<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cry of a stone, or, a treatise; shewing what is the right matter, forme, and government of the visible church of Christ. How, and wherein the present Church of England is wanting and defective, both in the body of the land, and in the parochiall branches thereof, with divers reasons and grounds taken from the Scriptures, to perswade all that feare God, rather to suffer any afflictions at the hands of men, than to submit to mans carnall policy and humane devices in the worship of God, or be deprived of the sweet fellowship of the saints in the right order of the Gospel. Together with a just reproofe of the over-strained and excessive separation, contentions and divisions of such as commonly are called Brownists. By Robert Coachman.</title>
            <author>Coachman, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 235 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79988</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4746</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E137_32</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208315</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867276</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867276</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119581</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79988)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119581)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 24:E137[32])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cry of a stone, or, a treatise; shewing what is the right matter, forme, and government of the visible church of Christ. How, and wherein the present Church of England is wanting and defective, both in the body of the land, and in the parochiall branches thereof, with divers reasons and grounds taken from the Scriptures, to perswade all that feare God, rather to suffer any afflictions at the hands of men, than to submit to mans carnall policy and humane devices in the worship of God, or be deprived of the sweet fellowship of the saints in the right order of the Gospel. Together with a just reproofe of the over-strained and excessive separation, contentions and divisions of such as commonly are called Brownists. By Robert Coachman.</title>
                  <author>Coachman, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Oulton and G. Dexter, and are to be sold at the Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Brownists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119581:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119581:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE CRY OF A STONE, OR, A TREATISE; SHEWING VVHAT IS THE RIGHT <hi>Matter, Forme,</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the viſible CHURCH of CHRIST.</p>
            <p>How, and wherein the preſent Church of <hi>England</hi> is wanting and defective, both in the body of the Land, and in the <hi>Parochiall</hi> branches thereof, With divers Reaſons and Grounds taken from the Scriptures, to perſwade all that feare GOD, rather to ſuffer any afflictions at the hands of men, than to ſubmit to mans carnall policy and humane devices in the worſhip of God, or be deprived of the ſweet fellowſhip of the Saints in the right order of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with a juſt reproofe of the over-ſtrained and exceſſive ſeparation, contentions and diviſions of ſuch as commonly are called <hi>Browniſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Robert Coachman.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jer. 15. 19.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>If thou take the pretious from the vile, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ou ſhalt be as my mouth.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ezra 4. 3.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is not for you, but for us to build an houſe to the Lord God of Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 50. 16. 17.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>What haſt thou to doe to take my Covenant in thy mouth, ſeeing tbou hateſt nurture?</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Oulton</hi> and <hi>G. Dexter,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Stationers,</hi> 1642.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119581:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119581:2"/>
            <head>A FORE-SPEECH To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is neither to get moncy nor credit, gentle Reader, that I have underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken this taske, and written this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe; for I am neither in name nor in truth ſo famous as to gaine either of theſe by writing, but even ſimple neceſsitie, and the violent conviction of truth and mine owne conſcience hath drawne me thereunto; and I know, that if I have any reward in this world, it will be none other then to be reckoned and rewarded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst thieves and malefactors, but let God doe what him pleaſeth.</p>
            <p>It grieveth mee much, that no man of greater eminence and learning will take in hand this taske, that could have done it better, and alſo with much better acceptation then ten thouſand ſuch as my ſelfe is; but what ſhall I ſay? ſince they all hold their peace, let this be accounted as the confuſed murmure, or <hi>Cry of a Stone,</hi> which uttereth a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 40</note> (though unknowne) language, when they that
<pb facs="tcp:119581:3"/> treade upon it with high lookes, are both deafe and dumbe.</p>
            <p>Indeed, theſe matters concerning the right ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering, conſtituting and governing the Church, are in our dayes matters of great difficulty, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the greateſt care and paines of the deepeſt wits, and greateſt learning that is amongst us; though not in it ſelf more difficult then other points, but becauſe of the ſtrong oppoſition of the times, which hath long ſtriven to darken the cleare light of the truth in theſe points, and to uphold humane de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and traditions, which in ſtead of truth, take up place in our time: That as the preaching of the death and reſurrection of Chriſt was to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> (that doted on carnall wiſdome) <hi>fooliſhneſſe;</hi> ſo in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 23.</note> our time, when more ſtate and glory is uſed for the gathering and governing of the Church, then ever Chriſt or his Apoſtles appointed, what marvell is it, though it ſeeme a baſe and fooliſh thing, to ſpeake of gathering the viſible Church of Chriſt by here and there a man out of countries and cities? when it is now no great matter to bring a whole Nation, conſiſting of divers millions of men and women, to be a viſible Church of Chriſt in one day. And indeed if ſuch wonders could be wrought, as are pretended, our Saviour Chriſt had a needleſſe feare if he ſhould come in our dayes, that made queſtion whether hee
<pb facs="tcp:119581:3"/> ſhould <hi>find faith on the earth,</hi> or not? For all our <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 8.</note> Nation is faithfull, and we need not cry out with <hi>David</hi> for help to God, becauſe <hi>not a godly man is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12. 1,</note> 
               <hi>left,</hi> but may rather ſtand forth and challenge the powers of hell, and ſay, beſtirre thee Divell, for here is ſcarce an ungodly man left.</p>
            <p>But if after all theſe loud boaſtings it be yet as hard to find faithfulneſſe &amp; ſincerity as ever it was, and that our ſtately Religion, be (in the moſt part) rather a ſuperſtitious cuſtome to breed ſecurity, then any matter of weight or worth to rejoyce in; and that Gods people are ſtill few, and ſcarce one of a hundred; if this be true, as heaven and earth knowes it to be true, then no man ſhould adventure upon the bare applauſe of the times, or common cuſtomes of the multitude; but ſhould try himſelfe by a more better and ſounder rule, leſt he run with the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the broad way that leads to death.</p>
            <p>But whom ſhall I appeale to for judgement of this booke? it is an old maxime, and a new Oracle; that the judgement of the vulgar is worth nothing, ſo as if it have no approbation of Divines, it may be carryed to the furnace.</p>
            <p>And as for the moſt part of our formall Schollers, who have ſet Divinity in the pillory, and wrote over it, <hi>The Church of England,</hi> &amp; make it their deepeſt ſtudy to ſet times and truth at unity, having by
<pb facs="tcp:119581:4"/> long cuſtome ſo clipped the holy tongue, that they cannot pronounce <hi>Shiboleth,</hi> but ſetting onely a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 12. 6.</note> face upon Religion, have like Water-men gone backeward ſo faſt from it, till they come betweene the conſumption of grace, and the aſſumption of preferment; from ſuch I muſt appeale, as no fit Judges in this controverſie, expecting rather that they ſhould be tormentors and butchers of all ſuch as call any of their formall courſes in queſtion, then be patient hearers of any thing that ſtriketh at their outward glory.</p>
            <p>Alſo for the Reformiſts, though their grounds <note place="margin">I uſe theſe names on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, not affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting it.</note> looke the ſame way that mine doe, yet many of them have ſuffered their eyes ſo to dazle upon their formall neighbours (who with a little yeelding to the times, ſit warme in their neſts, and live more like <hi>Princes</hi> than <hi>Apoſtles)</hi> that now they begin to call their owne wiſdome and ſoundneſſe in queſtion, and rather ſuſpect that their owne hearts have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them, then that the truth hath overſwayed them, and are mucb more willing to embrace any counſell that may procure them fleſhly liberty, then lend an eare to ought that ſhall perſwade them to a ſtricter or better courſe, and therefore I dare not permit them for Judges therein. Neither indeed is there any whom theſe times will acknowledge for a Divine, which is not more or leſſe tainted with the
<pb facs="tcp:119581:4"/> corruptions of this age, but if he be ſcrupulous, and will not ſwallow up all, and hold his tongue at that for whlch his heart ſmiteth him, hee may as well be canonized for a Saint in Rome, as regiſtred for a Divine in <hi>England,</hi> but ſhall paſſe under the terme of a <hi>puney</hi> or <hi>buſie fellow,</hi> notwithſtanding any gifts of <hi>learning</hi> or other <hi>endowments,</hi> that ſo the <hi>Argument</hi> of the <hi>Iewes</hi> againſt Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7. 48. may alwayes be in a readineſſe to ſtop the mouthes of the ſimple.</p>
            <p>And as little hope is there of any equall ſentence from any of the ſtrict ſeparation, ſeeing if a man agree with them in all points, ſave one onely (though it be but about hearing a Sermon in an old Temple) they will account him as bad as the worſt; If any ſhall like this project, they muſt ſurely be men of name, whatſoever they be of nature; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I may well ſay, <hi>I will appeale to no body,</hi> but onely to him that judgeth without reſpect of perſons.</p>
            <p>And in the meane time, I muſt account it my greate croſſe, that I muſt thus differ from ſo many learned and godly men in theſe points, and loth I was to doe it, but that neceſsity conſtrained mee, and the more, for that I ſee many <hi>Chriſtians</hi> intangled in the boughs of the tree, which never obſerve the cauſe that lyeth in the roote, being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that if they lived in a Church that in the body
<pb facs="tcp:119581:5"/> thereof were the feare of God, thoſe abuſes and corruptions would ſoone be remedied, but being otherwiſe, you may as well rob <hi>Micah</hi> of his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 18. 24</note> 
               <hi>Idolls,</hi> and heare no complaint, as you may ſtrip them of their corruptions, and heare no cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</p>
            <p>Three things there are required of him that ſhall oppoſe theſe evills of our dayes: Firſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of life, and a converſation unblameable, for elſe it is probable that his ſtrictneſſe in theſe points, proceedes rather from corruption than grace, that hath not taught himſelfe the <hi>great and weightie points of the Law,</hi> before he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 23.</note> with others for matters of leſſer moment, yea, and though hee uſe never ſo great wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of words, or weight of Argument, yet no great bleſsing of God, nor reverence of man can be expected upon his labours, who preacheth not as well with his converſation as with his lips.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing required, is an experimentall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> knowledge of the things ſtood for, beſide the evidence of Scripture, and force of reaſon; he that will diſtinctly diſcourſe of theſe things, and be able to refell the ſubtill evaſions and colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable gloſſes of the oppoſites, had need to have lived ſometime in a Church and fellowſhip of Saints under the pure Ordinances of the Goſpel,
<pb facs="tcp:119581:5"/> ſo ſhall hee be more ſenſible of the corruption and bondage which is in theſe Aſſemblies, and more ſettled to love and maintaine the purity and liberty of the Goſpell in the right order thereof.</p>
            <p>The third thing required, is, to <hi>count the</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 28</note> 
               <hi>coſt,</hi> and to have the price ready to lay downe whenſoever it is called for, be it goods, be it liberty, be it life; for ſhould a man be never ſo able to diſpute, and had never ſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and ſincerity in him, yet if alſo hee be not of a reſolved diſpoſition to ſuffer and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all that man can inflict upon him, and to ſeale with his blood what he hath written with his pen, or practiſed by his courſe, it will not much availe, though it be never ſo cleare and evident: Beſides, the Lord doth wonderfully advance his glory and Goſpell, by the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and blood of his ſervants, and giveth a <hi>bleſſed memoriall</hi> of them; but as for the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous and fearefull, that in all their profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions muſt <hi>make a faire ſhew in the fleſh,</hi> though <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 12.</note> they have the tongues of men and Angels, yet the <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Lord never much honoureth ſuch a prefeſsion.</p>
            <p>Now, how farre my ſelfe ſhall be found ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveable in theſe things may be queſtioned; and for me to ſpeake in praiſc of my ſelfe, were worſt
<pb facs="tcp:119581:6"/> of all; and it is ten times eaſier to give good counſell to others, than to follow it ones ſelfe; and confident and conceited men are more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten foyled when they come to examination and tryall, then thoſe that retaine in themſelves ſome feare and doubting.</p>
            <p>As touching my life and converſation, though <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the conſcience of mine owne infirmities which are open and bare before the All-ſeeing eye, might caſt mee upon the earth, and ſtop my mouth for ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ought, <hi>But God be mercifull to me a ſinner;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 13.</note> yet ſince by his grace I have beene kept in all my wanderings and temptations, from <hi>putting forth my hand to iniquity,</hi> or running into any <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125. 3.</note> ſcandalous evill, to the wounding of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſlander of Religion; why ſhould the operation of this grace be buryed in oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not rather be acknowledged to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall praiſe of his power and goodneſſe unto me?</p>
            <p>And as for my experience in the right order <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and conſtitution of the viſible Church, I ſerved an Apprentiſe of ten yeeres in a ſociety of as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Chriſtians, and under the pureſt orders and moſt profitable meanes that (I thinke) in this fraile life can be obtained. In which Church, though I were one <hi>of the leaſt of the leaſt of all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 8.</note> 
               <hi>the members,</hi> and from whom by ſimple neceſsity
<pb facs="tcp:119581:6"/> I was forced to depart; yet I was neither ſo <hi>idle</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 8.</note> 
               <hi>nor unprofitable</hi> amongst them, but that the things which paſſed there, made ſome impreſsion in me, which I truſt ſhall not be worne out whileſt I live; neither am I ſo ungratefull to my friends, or unmercifull to my Countrey-men, or ſo careleſſe of the honour of Chriſt, that I ſhould bury in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 4.</note> 
               <hi>thoſe worthy things</hi> which I have learned and ſeene, and which would at one inſtant put an end to many endleſſe controverſies and intangle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wherewith my Chriſtiſtian countrey-men are ſnared, and know not how to get out of them.</p>
            <p>And although there be many more fitter to handle theſe things, and more able to ſuffer for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> them; yet ſince <hi>all our ſufficiencie is from God,</hi> I deſpaire not wholly of my ſelfe, but truſt that <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 15.</note> for the furtherance of his glory, his power ſhall be perfected by my weakneſſe, and that I ſhall be made able through him with patience, yea, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 35.</note> 
               <hi>with joy to ſuffer</hi> the ſpoyling and loſſe of all that in this fraile ſtate is lent me.</p>
            <p>And though the time is come that judgement muſt begin <hi>at Gods Houſe,</hi> I truſt that I ſhall <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 17.</note> be content to be one of the firſt that ſhall leade <hi>the way to the ſhambles,</hi> and not feare to give my ſelfe to him that lent it mee, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44. 22.</note> to lay it downe for his glory on earth, which
<pb facs="tcp:119581:7"/> giveth me eternall glory in Heaven, which that I may doe in a right manner, and for a right end, as well as in a juſt cauſe, I earneſtly intreat the fervent ſupplications and prayers of all the Saints night and day for me, that I may indeede <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 41.</note> 
               <hi>that I am counted worthy</hi> to ſuffer for that part of the Goſpell, which this ſtately age will not endure to heare of.</p>
            <p>I have written very ſhort and briefe, partly for that this age having beene ſo long dulled with tedious volumes and diſcourſes can now brooke nothing but what runs poſt, and that which is briefe and various, partly that I might ſpend little time in writing, and avoyd great charge in printing; but principally becauſe I find, that things are eaſieſt underſtood, when they are ſet downe ſhortly, and when there is no enterlacings or ſurpluſage of words, more then barely to expreſſe the thing intended. I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured for a plaine and familiar ſtile, and yet avoyded light or affected phraſes; I have traduced no mans perſon, otherwiſe than as the things beare witneſſe againſt them, I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven all the honour to men that I may, <hi>with feare of my Maker:</hi> And if yet either the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 32. 22.</note> matter or manner be defective, or any thing out of joynt, remember ſtill it is but <hi>the Cry of a</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119581:7"/> 
               <hi>Stone,</hi> which never learned to ſpeake either La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine or Engliſh in any Schoole whatſoever: And take heed of ſtumbling over the truth, for ſome balkes in the way: but if the thing aimed at be the right ſetling of the Saints in the order of the Goſpel, otherwiſe than the vaine oſtentation and pompe of this age will permit, rather ſet thy ſelfe to helpe the Author to <hi>beare his croſſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 28</note> 
               <hi>and follow Chriſt in his temptations,</hi> then like <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 28.</note> a <hi>Sycophant,</hi> to ſit downe and ſcoffe at his wants of learning and eloquence.</p>
            <p>The Lord of his mercy pardon all our aberrations and failings, and give us grace to ſeeke him ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly in love and ſincerity, that our true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort may increaſe here, and our eternail comfort remaine hereafter.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> Robert Coachman.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="qualifications_and_definitions">
            <pb facs="tcp:119581:8"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>TO the end that the ingenuous and godly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of this Author <hi>(of reconciling theſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences betweene thoſe Chriſtians of the Engliſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, and thoſe of the Separation)</hi> may not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, obſerve, that in blaming the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and the Miniſtery thereof, hee doth not meane the perſonall Graces, Knowledge and Learning of any Chriſtians there; but he blames the confuſed manner of gathering Churches by houſe rowes of all ſorts: and by the Miniſtery, hee meanes the externall office conveyed to them by that authority which hee doth juſtly oppoſe.</p>
            <p>And when he ſpeaks of the Separation, hee is not againſt the cauſe, much leſſe the moderate way of the Churches of the Separation, nor their rejecting of the prophane world from thoſe privileges, proper and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to a viſible Church; as ſeales, cenſures, &amp;c. but he ſpeaks againſt thoſe perſonall errors of ſome who profeſſe ſeparation &amp; their erroneous opinions, who deny all viſible Chriſtians in the pariſh aſſemblies, and thereupon leave them in perſonall communion; as Prayer, Preaching, Conference, &amp;c. Now the God of all grace and mercy ſo diſpoſe of all his ſervants, that the great affaires of Jeſus Chriſt may not miſcary in their hands, but that they may at laſt ſo diſcover er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, that they may attain both peace and truth, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:119581:8"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS of the BOOKE.</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>OF the eſſentiall marks and notes of the viſible Church. pg. 1</item>
                  <item>2. The viſible Church hath right to all Gods Ordinances<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pg. 4</item>
                  <item>3. The Church or Churches of <hi>England</hi> cannot be juſtified. pg. 8</item>
                  <item>4. What Ordinances of God may be uſed in the pariſh aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and what not. pg. 10</item>
                  <item>5. It is no wrong to Gods people, when the carnall multitude is taxed, and they perſwaded to leave them. pg. 12</item>
                  <item>6. It is beſt for wicked men to be kept from the comforts of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation untill they repent. pg. 14</item>
                  <item>7. It is in vaine to ſeeke the reformation of a Church, when the Materialls are naught. pg. 16</item>
                  <item>8. It is a matter of great weight and neceſſity for Chriſtians to live in a right ordered Church. pg. 18</item>
                  <item>9. The reformed Churches are not condemned but admoniſhed by this ſtrict practice. pg. 22</item>
                  <item>10 The prohibition of the Magiſtrate, though he be a Chriſtian, may not hinder our obedience to the Goſpel. pg. 23</item>
                  <item>11. <hi>Moſes</hi> example in building the Tabernacle, was no ordinary rule for after times<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pg. 25</item>
                  <item>12. The examples of the Kings of Iſrael and Judah, in reſtoring Gods Worſhip, doe not binde to any faſhions in Religion, but Chriſts. pg. 26</item>
                  <item>13. A compariſon of the paterne of Chriſts Church with the Church of <hi>England.</hi> pg. 27</item>
                  <item>14. A proportionable application of the Jewes State, unto our times. pg. 28</item>
                  <item>15. The ſubmiſſion of the Jewes to the Heathen Kings, about building the Temple, is no imitable practice about the Church. pg. 30</item>
                  <item>16. The onely way to eſtabliſh the Goſpel and the pure Ordinances thereof is to ſuffer perſecution for it. pg. 31</item>
                  <item>17. The time of ſuffering is now come. pg. 32</item>
                  <item>18. Other motives to perſwade us to ſuffering. pg. 33</item>
                  <item>19. It is no ſtrange thing for Chriſtians to be perſecuted of Chriſtians. pg. 35</item>
                  <item>20. The ſcandalls in the ſeparated Churches is no Argument to condemne their practice. pg. 37</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119581:9"/>
            <p>The ſecond part.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>21. THe rigid Separation overrun their courſe in their firſt onſet. pg. 41</item>
                  <item>22. The generall Ohjection againſt hearing in the Pariſh aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies anſwered. pg. 43</item>
                  <item>23. What preaching it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and who may preach: as alſo where, and to whom. pg. 44</item>
                  <item>24. Of the libertie that the Word of God ought to have. pg. 45</item>
                  <item>25. The particular objections againſt hearing in the Pariſh aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies anſwered. pg. 47</item>
                  <item>26. Other objections againſt hearing anſwered. pg. 50</item>
                  <item>27. They that goe about to juſtifie the Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> in their office, drive men from the Church altogether. pg. 54</item>
                  <item>28. The ſtrict ſeparation cannot hold together amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. pg. 56</item>
                  <item>29. There are ſome ſinnes that muſt be borne in the Church. pg. 58</item>
                  <item>30. What kind of ſins and ſinners they be that may be borne in the Church. pg. 60</item>
                  <item>31. Three cautions concluding the Doctrine of forbearance. pg. 61</item>
                  <item>32. The Concluſion and Summe of all. pg. 63</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119581:9"/>
            <head>The CRY of a STONE.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the eſſentiall marks and notes of the viſible Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing that can rightly be deſcribed by any <note place="margin">SECT. 1.</note> ſpeciall Ornaments or priviledges thereof, but hee that will make a true and proper definition of any thing, muſt deſcribe it by ſuch properties as are ſo eſſentiall to the thing, as that being there, they make it to be that it is, and being abſent, it ceaſeth to be any more the ſame.</p>
               <p>The Church is often compared to a houſe, yea, called <hi>Gods</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Houſe:</hi> Now, no man can deſcribe a houſe by the ornaments and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture thereof, but onely by the matter and forme; both which being together, there is indeed a houſe, but if either be abſent, the houſe cannot be.</p>
               <p>Indeed, when materials are framed, wee ſometimes ſay, there is a houſe, though no forme appeare; but ſuch ſpeaking is improper, and it may rather be ſaid, there is ſtuffe for a houſe, then a houſe indeed: ſo in regard of the true materials of the Church, the people of God. whoſe hearts are framed to holineſſe and ſanctitie, dwelling here and there in the world, and never combining into a body, nor, perhaps, knowing they ſhould ſo doe, may yet be ſaid in an improper kind of ſpeaking, to be the Church of God; but this cannot be ſaid, but of the Church in generall and univerſall, combined and knit together <hi>by one ſpirit, partakers of one hope,</hi> and expecters of one glory.</p>
               <p>For touching the viſible Church, which preſents it ſelfe to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eye, the caſe is otherwiſe; and we may not account all viſible Chriſtians a viſible Church; for by a viſible Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wee meane a company or congregation aſſembling together. Now, a man may be a viſible Chriſtian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and never come at ſuch an aſſembly, much leſſe be a joyned member in the policie thereof.</p>
               <p>Neither doe we meane that every aſſembly or congregation is the Church of God, though the word be indifferently uſed; for there is <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26. 5. <hi>Act.</hi> 19. 41.</note> 
                  <hi>the Church of evill doers,</hi> and there is a <hi>Church</hi> of tumultuous railers.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119581:10"/>
               <p> In a word, the viſible Church of Chriſt, is a company of people ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally <note place="margin">The viſible Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</note> holy, or called Saints which combine and meet together, intending to performe the whole will and worſhip of God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as it is or ſhall be revealed to them.</p>
               <p>I ſay they are a company; for one man cannot be a Church, but <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> there muſt be <hi>two or three</hi> at leaſt, and not above ſuch a number, as <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 20.</note> may ordinarily meet together, and theſe muſt be externally <hi>holy,</hi> that is, ſuch as by their faith and converſation appeare unto men to be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Gods children and his <hi>elect;</hi> for of the heart onely God muſt be the judge; and if the profeſſion be ſound and the converſation honeſt in the outward appearance and manifeſtation, wee have not to doe to <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 7. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 4.</note> examine any further, but ought in charitie to judge men to be ſuch as outwardly they appeare, leaving ſecret things to God.</p>
               <p>I ſay further, that theſe Saints muſt combine and aſſemble together, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and that not by compulſion or accident, but <hi>voluntarily</hi> covenant and <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 25. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 14. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 9. 10.</note> gather together to performe with heart and tongue the whole will and worſhip of God for the building up of themſelves in all the knowne wayes of God, <hi>comforting the feeble minded, helping the weake, rectify the ſtragler, and convince the oppoſite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay (intending to performe the whole will of God) for they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> may at the firſt be ignorant of many things appertaining to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. 22.</note> of God, and yet be the Church of God: for it is with a Church in her minority, as with a Chriſtian at his firſt converſion, who hath onely a generall reſolution to doe the whole will of God, but the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. 33.</note> of that obedience, hee performeth by ſteps and degrees, as hee commeth to learne and underſtand them: ſo a company of godly men may become a Church, and performe with ſinceritie and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, ſuch things as they know and underſtand at the firſt, and when God giveth them further knowledge and meanes, to proceed to other practiſes, as the Chriſtian women in <hi>Philippi,</hi> who at the firſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together, having (as it ſeemeth) no other exerciſe but <hi>Prayer,</hi> and yet afterward there was a very compleate and famous Church of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 13. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 2.</note> Saints, having both <hi>Biſhops and Deacons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereſoever therefore there is an aſſembly of godly men knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and performing the worſhip of God (though but in part) it may truly be ſaid of them, as <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid of the ſervants of God, when he ſaw them marching ſo diligently, this is none other then <hi>Beth-el,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. 12. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>the houſe of God,</hi> this is a proper viſible Church.</p>
               <p>And whereſoever other aſſemblies are, then of faithfull Chriſtians, whatſoever ordinances of God they have, yet they ſtand them in no more ſtead then circumciſion did the <hi>Sichemites,</hi> but ſo often as they <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 34. 25.</note> take <hi>up the name of God,</hi> and performe any religious ſervice unto him, <hi>whileſt they hate</hi> to be reformed, ſo often they are guilty of uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 16, 17.</note> and intruſion upon that which appertaineth not to them, and are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119581:10"/> manifeſt takers of Gods name in vaine, whom he will <hi>not hold guiltleſſe.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>They therefore are much miſtaken, who deſcribe and marke out the Church by the Ordinances; for as circumciſion availed not the <hi>Sichemites,</hi> nor the <hi>Arke</hi> of God the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> even ſo the moſt glorious <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5. 4, 9.</note> Ordinances of God being uſed by ſuch as are not his children, are as a <hi>Parable in the mouth of a foole,</hi> and ſo farre they are from making wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men Gods Church, as that the more they uſe them before they <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 8.</note> have faith and grace, the greater is their ſinne, and the further off they are from being either Gods Church or children.</p>
               <p>The preaching of the Word can be no mark of the viſible Church, otherwiſe than as it is an effectual inſtrument to prepare men therun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; <note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 18. 19. 25. <hi>and</hi> 22. 19. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 22, <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 3. 4, 5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 19, 20.</note> for it was preached amongſt <hi>Baals Prophets,</hi> and amongſt the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Ninivites, Babylonians, &amp;c.</hi> yet were neither of theſe Gods Church or people. <hi>Noah</hi> preached powerfully to the old world, yet were they not Gods Church. The <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> have had the Word preached to them, yet no man will ſay they are the viſible Church of Chriſt, neither can the Sacraments be any marke of the Church at all, ſince they make nothing to be which was not the ſame before, but onely <note place="margin">The Word and Sacraments no markes of the viſible Church.</note> confirme ſomething which before was. A <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Frier with a ſcoupe baptized a thouſand ſilly <hi>Indians</hi> at one time, which were drawne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by a ſtratagem, were theſe now any thing the more Gods Church; and if he ſhould have given them the other Sacrament alſo, had it availed any thing the more, or if in ſtead of this Frier there had been one of the moſt godlieſt Miniſters in all <hi>Europe,</hi> had it not beene all one, ſo long as the people had not faith nor grace? ſo that it is plain, that holy people, and not holy ordinances give the being to the viſible Church, &amp; it is no more an argument to prove a company of carnall and irreligious people to be Gods Church, becauſe they have amongſt them his ſacred ordinances, then a true mans purſe in the hand of a thiefe is an argument to prove a thiefe a true man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119581:11"/>
               <head>The viſible Church hath right to all Gods Ordinances.</head>
               <p>IT is then a ſocietie of religious and faithfull people, that have right <note place="margin">SECT. 2.</note> to Gods ſpirituall Ordinances, and ſuch onely may, and muſt uſe them, ſo farre as they are able. They are all of them to ſtrive to <hi>attaine the beſt gifts, and eſpecially to propheſie,</hi> yea, and if it were poſſible, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 1. 2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>to be Doctors,</hi> and that not in bare conceit, but in truth and ſoundneſſe, and ſuch amongſt them as excell in gifts and graces they are <hi>much to love and reverence,</hi> and alſo to encourage them to the orderly uſe of the <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 18.</note> grace they have received, without <hi>hiding their talent, that ſo all may learne and receive comfort.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">&amp; 14. 29. 30. 31</note>
               </p>
               <p>And becauſe all good men have not one and the ſame gift, therefore every one is adviſedly to conſider, what his portion is, and what he may take to, and where he muſt ſtay, that none run beyond their line, preſume above <hi>that which is meet.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Some have the gift of utterance, and are fluent in ſpeech, others a gift of diſcerning to judge of that which is uttered: ſome are excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 4. 5. 6.</note> in prayer, others are ſweet in ſinging, ſome are apt to move pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable <note place="margin">The gifts of the Church.</note> queſtions, others prompt in anſwering them, ſome can diſpute very profitably, others can receive much helpe by diſputation, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And many times they which are of little manifeſtation, and leaſt ſeene to meddle in publique paſſages are moſt holy and ſtrict in their converſation, whoſe examples doe often times <hi>preach</hi> as profitably as if <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 7. 8.</note> they had the greateſt fluencie of ſpeech that could be.</p>
               <p>Neither muſt the Saints be envious againſt one another, becauſe they have not one and the ſame gift: for one and the ſame ſpirit worketh diverſly in all the members of the Church, that this ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all body may be compleate, and performe all ſpirituall <hi>offices;</hi> as the naturall body hath divers members, and all for ſeverall <hi>offices,</hi> much leſſe may any hide their talent, becauſe it is not of the ſame meaſure with others; ſince he which had but one talent was required to traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 26. 27.</note> as well as he that had five, and all the ſervants are commanded to <hi>watch</hi> as well (though not ſo much) as the <hi>Porter.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 13. 24. 27</note>
               </p>
               <p>This viſible Church of Saints ſtand bound and tied each to other, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> not onely by the common rule of Chriſtianity; but by their very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporating and combining together into a Church State, or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall policie, from which naturally or neceſſarily ariſeth that which we call the Diſcipline, or power which is independent amongſt themſelves, for the curing <hi>and purging</hi> of ſin and ſinners that breake <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 7.</note> out amongſt them into any enormous or ſcandalous practice.</p>
               <p>For as in cities and corporations, each member carefully obſerveth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119581:11"/> whether his neighbour obſerve the rules of the Charter wherunto he <note place="margin">The power of the Church.</note> is ſworne, and upon default in matter of weight, the partie offending is either disfranchized, or otherwiſe corrected civilly; ſo in this bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood or ſpirituall policie of the Church, each man obſerveth, as himſelfe, ſo his fellow members, that if any find his brother to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe againſt the heavenly Charter, and Covenant made with God and his people, he reproveth and admoniſheth him lovingly betwixt them <hi>two alone,</hi> and if it be any capitall or ſcandalous evill, and that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 15. 16 17.</note> he will not repent of it, then the brother offended, taketh with him <hi>one or two,</hi> to helpe, convince and reprove the ſinner, and to witneſſe both the fact, and the due proceeding thereabout; and if hee will not hearc them ſo as to repent, then to complaine to the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereof hee is a member, that ſo being <hi>rebuked of many,</hi> hee may <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 6.</note> yet at laſt be aſhamed, and give God the glory, and ſo receive for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of God and men. But if hee will not heare nor regard the Church, nor in reverence to that ſacred meanes of his recovery, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and humble himſelfe for his ſinne, then the Church with humble <hi>and ſorrowfull</hi> hearts muſt cut him off as a decayed member, and deliver him unto Satan, that ſo that proud and corrupt fleſh may <hi>be deſtroyed, and the ſpirit ſaved in the day of the Lord Ieſus.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Provided ſtill, that all theſe proceedings be in love, lenitie and compaſſion, and that no man be brought to the Church, much leſſe <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 14.</note> cenſured; for infirmities and failing in judgement, or for matters in our times doubtfull and controverſall, but for matters of weight, and ſuch evills as being perſiſted in, doe out of doubt, ſhut the party out of heaven, of which more hereafter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>And for their more better and orderly proceeding in the uſe of all the Ordinances of God in the Church, they are as ſoone as any, fit <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> men riſe out of them, or joyne unto them, to make choice of ſome for their Biſhops, Paſtors or Elders, upon whom they muſt ordinarily <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 6. 7.</note> depend, for the diſpenſing of the Word, Prayer and Sacraments; as alſo to rule, guide, and goe before them in their conſultations decrees, and execution of Diſcipline, and all other publique buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe Biſhops or Elders may not intrude themſelves into their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. 1. 2. Miniſters elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Act.</hi> 6. 3. 5. and 14. 23. Ordination of the miniſters. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 22.</note> and miniſtrations, by any forreigne or civill power, but muſt <hi>be choſen</hi> by that Church and ſocietie <hi>of Saints</hi> in which they are to adminiſter.</p>
               <p>Their ordination or putting in poſſeſſion, muſt be with giving a charge to them, with ſome ſigne, either of giving the hand, or <hi>laying hands</hi> upon their heads, which may be done either by the Elders of ſome other Church, who as brethen may aſſiſt and helpe their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, ſo farre as they can; or rather by ſome principall man amongſt <note place="margin">No ſucceſſion of any univerſall Miniſterie now.</note> themſelves: ſince it cannot be imagined with any ſhew of reaſon, that there is any univerſall Miniſtery ſince the Apoſtles dayes, neither
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119581:12"/> any that can execute their office out of that particular flocke where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the <hi>holy Ghoſt hath made them overſeers,</hi> no more then the Lord Major <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 28.</note> of <hi>London</hi> may goe and execute juſtice in the Citie of <hi>Yorke,</hi> of which more hereafter.</p>
               <p>And although in the Common-wealth, a Lordly and Imperious <note place="margin">Miniſters no Lords 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 3.</note> rule may be tollerable, yet the Miniſterie of the Church is of another nature, and may not be imagined to be any matter of State, or to ſtand for any carnall pompe, but is a matter of meet ſervice, and they <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 5. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 12. <hi>Act.</hi> 6. 4. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 2.</note> are conſtantly to <hi>labor</hi> in ſpirituall works in all humility &amp; patience, <hi>giving themſelves</hi> wholy to their miniſtrations, and <hi>ſtudying to approve</hi> themſelves to every mans conſcience in <hi>the ſight of God.</hi> Neither is their office for name and forme, but for the preſervation of order and comlineſſe in Church Ordinances, that all the rights and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Church may be uſed and continued in a grave and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iy manner, as they are excellent in their ſubſtance and matter.</p>
               <p>And as theſe Biſhops or Elders are to preach conſtantly the Word, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> both on the Lords Day, and other times of the Churches meetings, <note place="margin">The Miniſters muſt ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Saints in the Church.</note> and to adminiſter the Sacraments in both kinds upon the members of the Church, as there is occaſion; as alſo to execute and declare the publique decrees, determinations and cenſures of the Church: So they are not any way to infringe the liberty of the Saints, or ingroſſe their privileges, but ſtill to foſter &amp; cheriſh all thoſe ſeverall gifts and graces which are in all, or any of the members. They muſt ſtill up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and maintaine in the Church the ſtoole of the Prophets, and to have in great eſteeme <hi>Propheſying</hi> or preaching by men of gifts and <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 1. 2.</note> aptneſſe, though not in office, that ſo all may learne and increaſe, that ſo fit and able men may be bred up in the Church, whom the body <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 5. 6.</note> may appoint into office of Miniſterie in after times, or when any of their officers ſhall any way faile.</p>
               <p>Neither may the Elders deprive the Saints of their lawfull and Chriſtian libertie in their elections, rejections or determinations in <note place="margin">3 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 10.</note> the Church by any fore-ſtallings, repreſſings, inſultings, or preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but contenting themſelves with meeke and grave counſell to goe before the reſt in their proceedings; and if the body of the Church ſhall not agree to that which the officers ſhall thinke beſt, that yet the officers thinke it no diſparagement to their eminencie, or honour to be overſwayed, and led beſide their mindes and purpoſes ſometimes by the body of the Church, whoſe ſervants they are, knowing, that where the honour and order of God is obſerved, no man can truly receive any dammage.</p>
               <p>And as the viſible Church muſt continue their aſſembling and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> communicating together in all actions for the ſoule, ſo the duties of love, and their communion in temporall things for the body may in <note place="margin">The Churches benevolence.</note> no wiſe be neglected, whileſt this fraile life laſteth, which commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119581:12"/> 
                  <hi>in giving and receiving,</hi> though it be no religious action in it ſelfe, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Philip.</hi> 4. 15. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2. 22.</note> yet is it of ſuch ſimple neceſſitie and affinitie thereunto, as that it may no more be ſevered from religion, then good workes may be ſeverd from <hi>faith;</hi> and for their more eaſie, and ſubſtantiall doing theſe duties, and relieving the wants of their brethren, they are o <hi>looke out wiſe</hi> and <hi>truſtie</hi> men, from <hi>amongſt themſelves,</hi> whom they are <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 6. 3. 5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 10.</note> to chooſe and appoint to this buſineſſe, and to whom they muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their money and treaſure, and to whoſe wiſedome and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <note place="margin">The Deacons office.</note> they muſt referre the diſtribution and diſpoſing of thoſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things.</p>
               <p>And in this contribution the Saints whom God hath <hi>bleſſed</hi> with <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> any portion of this worlds goods muſt accordingly extend their mercifull liberality with all <hi>cheerefulneſſe,</hi> yea, and if need ſo require, <hi>to ſell even their lands and goods,</hi> and whatſoever they have to relieve <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 45. <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 33.</note> the wants of their poore brethren, without any murmuring or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, remembring, that the life of a Chriſtian is more precious then any thing elſe in this world.</p>
               <p>This diſtribution of the Churches benevolence, muſt be to the Elders that toyle in the Word and Doctrine, as alſo to the poore, aged, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 11. 12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 10.</note> ſicke, and helpleſſe perſons, eſpecially thoſe of the houſhold of Faith, that ſo the will of God may be done, and all comfort and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given to the poore Saints, as alſo all murmuring complaints and outcries prevented, by which it may be ſaid, (and that not without <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 6. 1.</note> cauſe) that the Church hath pietie, but no pitie.</p>
               <p>Neither is the widowes office to be forgotten as a needleſſe thing, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> but if it fall out that amongſt the Church there be found ſome aged <note place="margin">The widdowes office.</note> and <hi>grave widowes</hi> who are looſed from the bands of wanton youth, and have <hi>age</hi> upon them <hi>as a crowne of glory,</hi> being yet healthy, cheerefull, and ſtrong, the Church is there to chooſe and appoint them for <hi>Deaconeſſes,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 16. 31.</note> or tenders of the ſick, and to allow them ſuch reliefe and maintenance, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 9. 10 <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 1. 2.</note> as is needfull and fit, knowing that in ſickeneſſe there is required much labour and paines, and moſt neede of comfort and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement.</p>
               <p>And thus the Church and people of God, goe hand in hand, both in ſickneſſe and in health, in poverty and in wealth, in adverſitie and proſperitie, rejoycing together, weeping together, and being of like <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 15. 16</note> affection, in a ſweet and heavenly ſympathie, holding out in adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 8.</note> without ſhrinking, and perſevering in proſperity with all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119581:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Church or Churches of</hi> England <hi>cannot be iuſtified.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd if this be the right patterne of the viſible Church of Chriſt, <note place="margin">SECT. 3.</note> according to the Goſpel, then let us turne our eyes upon our ſelves, and ſee what reſemblance there is amongſt us of theſe Apoſtolique orders, and upon notice taken of our defects, let us ſee if they may not be amended.</p>
               <p>And firſt, whereas the materialls of the Church of the Goſpel are none other then a company of converted people gathered <hi>out of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 35. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17. 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19, 20. <hi>Acts</hi> 18. 11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 15. &amp; 11. 2. 17.</note> and from the world, our nation, and our world is all one with the Church, and hee that is of one, is, or muſt be of the other; the Apoſtles firſt <hi>preached and converted men,</hi> and afterward united them into a <hi>Church;</hi> but we firſt unite the whole nation into the Church, and feed them all with the pledges and ſeales of Gods love, and then goe about to convert them, afterward by preaching judgement to <note place="margin">Our Churches defective in their matter.</note> them; but this is rather to ſcatter then to gather with Chriſt, and is more like the Papiſts pompe, then the Apoſtles plainneſſe; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God did once chooſe a whole nation, which firſt were in the loynes <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5. 5.</note> and family of <hi>Abraham,</hi> yet that nation being broken off from God, no nation can now ſucceed them, nor can challenge that right <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 37. &amp; 7. 6, 7.</note> to be Gods people, otherwiſe then they are found converted, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and obey the Goſpel, which that a whole nation conſiſting of many millions of people, ſhould doe in one day ſhould be ſtrange and miraculous, and the way to heaven muſt ceaſe to be ſtrait, if ſo many can walke in it at conce.</p>
               <p>And if any ſhall think otherwiſe, let them ſhew when the generall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> body of this Land (which are counted the Church of <hi>England)</hi> was better then now they are, yea, and now after ſixtie yeeres preaching the Goſpell, whether the greater part be not yet apparantly <hi>in their ſins,</hi> and unconverted, and doe not indeed apparantly oppoſe and fight againſt ſuch as are ſincere and faithfull, contemning and deſpiſing all admonition and counſell, and ſerve not the Lord, <hi>but ſerve Satan</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 12.</note> and their owne luſts; and therefore the generall multitude of this nation cannot in any ſenſe be ſaid to be Gods people, or the true and proper matter of the viſible Church.</p>
               <p>And if we ſhall deſcend at once to the pariſh aſſemblies, which are the branches of this nationall Church, and looke upon them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitely, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> wee ſhall finde them of the ſame ſtampe with the nation, though no doubt ſome of them which have long enjoyed powerfull <note place="margin">The pariſh mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted.</note> preaching, are much more reformed then others; but taking them one with another, they are for the moſt part of the people ignorant,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119581:13"/> prophane and ſcandalous, being common ſwearers, liers, drunkards, quarrellers, wantons, Atheiſts, and even as their <hi>owne Prophets</hi> have truely complained of them: and as hee that travelleth amongſt them <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 12.</note> about his affaires ſhall finde them, and whileſt the moſt of them are ſuch, who can juſtifie their eſtate, but he ſhall make himſelfe abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to God; and every time hee goeth about to juſtifie them, as <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 17. 15.</note> Gods people, and Church, his owne heart ſhall give him the lye nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther availeth it to ſay, they are baptized and profeſſe the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for if they have all the Baptiſmes and Ordinances that ever were or are, and profeſſed never ſo much truth in words, yet whileſt they <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet</hi> 1. 19. 20. 21, 22.</note> are wicked in their deeds and lives, they are but ſo much the more the children of hell for their knowledge and profeſſion, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Turks are in farre better caſe then they. Secondly, indeed they profeſſe no Religion at all, nor may in any ſenſe be called Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors; when doe they profeſſe or ſpeake of any Religion or mention the name of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> unleſſe it be in their ſwearing or vain talking: their profeſſion is the ſervice of the Divell, <hi>who is their father,</hi> and under <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 44.</note> whoſe tutorſhip they are notable Schollers. Thirdly, if any thing make them Profeſſors, it is their comming to Church now and then, to lend an eare to ſome inſtruction, and ſuch profeſſors might a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Turkes</hi> be, if they were in <hi>England,</hi> and would either for feare of Law, cuſtome or faſhion, come ſometimes to the aſſembly, though ſtill they returned to their old vomit, and never left off their <hi>old ſinnes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 9.</note> and vices; ſo that whatſoever can be alledged for them, untill they repent and turne from their wicked courſes, all ſuch pleas were as good be never a whit as never the better.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Neither can the goodneſſe of ſome few that are in the pariſh help to ſalve the matter, no more then <hi>Lots</hi> being in <hi>Sodome</hi> could juſtifie the <hi>Sodomites:</hi> for thoſe godly are amongſt them but as a condemned or deſpiſed people, which ſcarce dare ſhew themſelves in their pious arts, but are overtopped and held under by the vaine multitudes in all places. Indeed, temporall puniſhments may be with-held, for the righteous ſakes, as in <hi>Sodome,</hi> but that the ſpirituall State of the carnall <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 38.</note> multitude ſhould be good becauſe of the preſence of ſome few good men is no more like then that <hi>Ioram</hi> and his complices were juſtified, <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 3. 13, 14.</note> by the preſence of <hi>Eliſha</hi> and <hi>Iehoſaphat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither will the badneſſe of the <hi>Iewes</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate in Chriſts time and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore under the <hi>Law,</hi> juſtifie this confuſed Church of the Goſpell. For, firſt as it is a bad plea to juſtifie one evill by another: ſecondly ſo we muſt ſtill remember that God now chooſeth no more whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons but ſelecteth his Saints out of all nations: thirdly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the covenants <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 7, 8.</note> of the <hi>Iewes</hi> were abſolutely temporall and ſpirituall, and the promiſes to be believed for this life properly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but our covenants that God maketh with us, are onely ſpiritually abſolute, and the promiſes for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119581:14"/> this life, are onely conditionall: Fourthly, <hi>Gods face,</hi> and the ſeat of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 28. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 21. 23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 20.</note> that Church was to be ſought in the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> or <hi>Temple:</hi> but now there is no place priviledged or exempted, but where <hi>two or three are gathered in Chriſts Name, hee is in the middeſt of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude, as the Kingdome of Satan is every where in this world, and as the Lord by outward manifeſtation <hi>differenceth</hi> his choſen ones <hi>from the world,</hi> and them within from them without: ſo <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 12. 13.</note> muſt wee every where put difference betwixt the <hi>righteous</hi> and the wicked, and beware of ſaying to the <hi>wicked, thou art righteous,</hi> or giving <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>holy things to dogs,</hi> or partaking with them, or joyning to them in their devouring <hi>pearles,</hi> or afford them our fellowſhip, when they <hi>uſurpe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>upon</hi> ſuch ordinances as are peculiar to Gods Elect and Faithfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>What Ordinances of God may be uſed in the Pariſh aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and what not.</head>
               <p>YEt ſo long as life laſteth there may be ſome hope of recovery, neither are we to deſpaire of any, though never ſo vile, but <note place="margin">SECT. 4.</note> that they may be converted and turned to God; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were are ſtill as with patience to ſuffer the evill men, ſo to prove alwayes, if at any time they may be brought out of the ſnare of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Divell; and for this end it is very neceſſary that the preaching of the <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 24. 25. The Word may be preached to evill men.</note> Word be amongſt them both publikely and privately, if they will but be brought to it, and have the patience to heare themſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and convinced by it; for as wee know it to be the onely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary meanes for their converſion; ſo alſo wee ſee that many are daily by it converted and brought home unto God, and ſo farre I <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 14.</note> am from diſliking the preaching of the Word to them, as that I would have them heare it where it is moſt purely and powerfully taught, and wiſh, that where there is one ſuch Preacher, there were a hundred.</p>
               <p>But untill they doe convert and turne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> none of the ſeales muſt in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> any eaſe be adminiſtred to them or their ſeed, neither are they to be admi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed as members into the Church &amp; fellowſhip of the Saints, nor <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 26. 27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 17. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1. 13. 14.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>each any thing to others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor take up the name of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>blations or ſacrifices to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> untill they have cleanſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ntance much leſſe are the faithfull to partake with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ophaning of the Sacraments. But if by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> his ſtrength they have gotten a cuſtome <note place="margin">T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſacred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>inances and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119581:14"/> to their cuſtomes, nor have ought to doe with them in their taking the Name and Ordinances of God in vaine; for the proper ends of the ſeals are to confirm and comfort the faithfull, and ſuch as groan under their ſinnes; but how can the ſeale be ſet, or the aſſurance given to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 28.</note> them that have not faith, neither are wearied with their ſinnes, but love and delight in them. And how can any godly man conſent in, or ſay Amen to ſuch an holy action, when it is joyntly done by ſuch as for the moſt part are Gods enemies; for the ſpirituall ſupper of the Lord is not like other civill banquets wherein civill fellowſhip and <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 13.</note> naturall refreſhing is properly aimed at, but the fellowſhip therein is ſpirituall, and they that feaſt at it, muſt be united to Chriſt by one ſpirit, but now carnall men have not the ſpirit, and ſo can be no gueſts at that banquet.</p>
               <p>This banquet is even the neereſt fellowſhip that the Saints can have in this world, and moſt reſembleth heaven; and it is not onely a ſure pledge of their fellowſhip with Chriſt, but alſo a demonſtration of their unity together, as the Apoſtle teacheth. But what a many <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 17.</note> lying ſignes and deceiveable demonſtrations doe ſuch Chriſtians make, that communicate they care not where, nor with whom, but thinke if they examine themſelves, it is enough, forgetting that it is an act of communion, and ſo called by the Apoſtle, and though the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> terme of a holy thing be given to it, yet if wee ſever the word Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from communion, wee put out Gods termes, and place in our owne.</p>
               <p>Many diſlike that the godly ſhould be civilly familiar with vaine and irreligious perſons, but to be ſtrict in that, and allow them to ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet with all manner of perſons at the heavenly ſupper of the Lord, is even as current counſell, as theirs who ſaid, it was nothing to <hi>ſweare</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>by the Temple,</hi> but to ſweare by the gold of the Temple was a treſpaſſe; for if there be any act in this world that declares Chriſtian ami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, peace and ſweet friendſhip in the grace of the Goſpell, this doth it, when wee ſit and feaſt together with Chriſt at his Table, and eate his fleſh, and drinke his blood.</p>
               <p>As Chriſt therefore preached the Goſpel to all ſorts of men good and bad, but when he adminiſtred the ſupper, hee drew out ſuch as were apparantly <hi>faithfull and godly.</hi> So now, the Word may be preached <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 11. 14. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13. 30.</note> and heard amongſt the worſt miſcreants that are, but when wee goe to ſit with <hi>Chriſt at his Table,</hi> let us know (as farre as wee can by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance) what gueſts goe with us.</p>
               <p>Neither may theſe wicked men have any cenſure of excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation executed upon them, much leſſe execute it upon one another: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <note place="margin">The power of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion belongs not to the pariſh multitudes.</note> for, they were never in covenant with Chriſt, and ſo have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o covenant, nor can be puniſhed for any breach of covenant, but were ever as they are, <hi>naught from the wombe,</hi> and downeright unbeliever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119581:15"/> ſtill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Secondly, what have they to doe to cenſure others, when they are as ill themſelves? May one adulterer or drunkard or ſwearer, <hi>caſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>a ſtone</hi> at another, when hee is as bad himſelfe as the worſt? Thirdly, if they ſhould ſo doe were it any more then a mockery: as if the thieves at <hi>Gods hill</hi> ſhould hold a ſeſſion to hang the cut-purſes, which were an onely way to make ſinne to be counted a trifle, and a jeſt, rather then to be feared and trembled at: it is onely the Saints that may binde them that are mighty in evill, and none other have this <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. 8, 9.</note> honour.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, ſeeing excommunication is for the deſtruction of the fleſh <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 5.</note> (ſuppoſing the perſon to have the ſpirit, though overwhelmed by the corruption of nature, how can it be exerciſed on them which ſtill were and are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> altogether fleſh? For if their fleſh be deſtroyed, the whole man is deſtroyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>It is no wrong to Gods people, when the carnall multitude is taxed, and they perſwaded to leave them.</head>
               <p>IF now upon theſe and the like conſiderations wee leave the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <note place="margin">SECT. 5.</note> and carnall multitudes in the pariſh aſſemblies, in all ſuch <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> actions, as are proper and peculiar to the faithfull, and in feare of offending God and ſtrengthening his enemies in evill, we joyne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſtian fellowſhips apart from them, what hurt of injury doe we to any? what hurt was it to <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> when <hi>Eliſha</hi> in his preſence proteſted againſt <hi>Ioram,</hi> as againſt one betweene whom and God, he <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 3. 13. 14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 14. <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 52. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 27. It is no fault to taxe wicked men, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them.</note> would not intercede? what hurt was it to Chriſts Diſciples<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when their naturall friends the <hi>Iewes,</hi> were taxed by Chriſt, and called blind guides, <hi>and blind leaders of the blind, diſſemblers, hypocrites, &amp;c.</hi> So when we tax here the multitude of carnall people, and proteſt againſt them that they are not Gods children<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor that they have no right to his ſacred ordinances, nor to come neere his altar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor uſe his name and word, untill they repent. But that thoſe holy and conſecrated things belong onely to the faithfull Chriſtians of which there are many in the aſſemblies, whom we tell that they are not in their proper place, nor right fellowſhip, but ought to <hi>withdraw themſelves</hi> from that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 40. 41. 44. 47.</note> in all ſuch actions as are proper to the Saints and unite them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the fellowſhip of godly men, with whom they may freely and comfortably participate, in the ſweet myſteries of the Lord; doe wee in this ſpeake blaſphemie? and are wee worthy for ſuch words and practiſes, to be taxed and traduced in print and pulpit; for wicked and <hi>damnable Schiſmatiques?</hi> For what Chriſtian man is there,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119581:15"/> that had not rather converſe with godly men then ungodly? are not <note place="margin">It is no fault to aſſociate onely with the godly in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> the preſence of faithfull Chriſtians ſweeter to a Chriſtian, when hee commeth to powre out his prayers, and offer his oblations than the ſociety of carnall men? Well then, what is the matter, that wee for holding and practiſing theſe things, muſt be thus toſſed about and abuſed? Why muſt we be put in priſon, confiſcate goods, goe into exile, and death for holding and practiſing no otherwiſe than every <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 3.</note> Chriſtian ſoule in heart deſireth? we would begin our heavenly har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony here &amp; our delight ſhould be <hi>only in the Saints<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and it is cuſtome, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tailor</hi> on <hi>Titus, pag.</hi> 691.</note> wit and art, that fighteth againſt grace, conſcience and Scripture; and it is they out of their <hi>idle viſions,</hi> that perſwade to give holy things to <hi>Dogs,</hi> and mingle <hi>light and darkneſſe, Chriſt and Belial together;</hi> and <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 14. 15. and 5. 10.</note> though times favour theſe abuſes, and puniſh us for our right groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded aſſertions, yet anon we ſhall come before a moſt juſt Judge, and then wee ſhall ſee whoſe righteouſneſſe and juſt judgement ſhall be <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 6.</note> brighteſt, and who hath gone the righteſt courſe.</p>
               <p>Wee labour to juſtifie the righteous, and condemne the ungodly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and would not have the honourable name of Chriſtians or godly <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9. 10. 11.</note> men, given to <hi>ſwearers, liers, drunkards, oppreſſors, ſlanderers, &amp;c.</hi> but would have them know, that as they live and delight in ſinne, and <hi>hate to be reformed;</hi> ſo no comfort, no priviledge nor favour belongs <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 16.</note> unto them in that eſtate, but till they repent and breake off their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly courſes, no peace can be to them, nor no fellowſhip in the ſeales and badges of Saints can be had with them but as they are of the world, ſo we muſt account them, and under the kingdome of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. 3.</note> and it belongeth not <hi>to them, but unto us to build an houſe</hi> to the Lord our God, unto them belongs no promiſe of any favour till they repent, but onely the Law, thereatnings, judgements, commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and ſharpe rebukes, which they are alwayes to heare, both publikely and privately, upon all occaſions, but nothing muſt ever be ſaid or done to them, by which they have any cauſe to thinke they are in Gods favour before they turne from their ſinnes; for if the <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 18.</note> moſt <hi>righteous ſcarcely,</hi> and with much adoe, <hi>be ſaved, where ſhall ſuch wicked and ſinners appeare,</hi> and what hope is there for them?</p>
               <p>And ſeeing in the things of this life they have their <hi>eaſe, pleaſure and</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>priviledges</hi> above the godly, what are then the priviledges of the <hi>Saints?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 2. 3. <hi>Iob</hi> 21. 9. 10.</note> if alſo in ſpirituall ordinances and heavenly prerogatives they are equallized with them; alas, the men of this world feaſt and laugh, and dominere in their purple, ſcarlet, and fleſhly wantonneſſe, when ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 23. 30. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 11. 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 12.</note> of Gods deare children weepe and mourne in ſecret before the Lord, and are faine to pinch hard, goe thin, lie in priſon, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times goe to the ſhambles, that they may be tryed as gold in the fire, and all the privileges of the Saints, is their free acceſſe <hi>to God,</hi> their fellowſhip in their Sabbaths, Sacrifices, Prayers, bleſſings, ſeales<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119581:16"/> 
                  <hi>new ſongs</hi> of praiſe, in all which they meet with Chriſt their Saviour, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 99. 1. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 21.</note> and ſo gather new comfort and refreſhing daily, amidſt the many croſſes and troubles of this tranſitory world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>It is beſt for wicked men to be kept from the comforts of ſalvation, untill they repent.</head>
               <p>IF wicked men be offered no meanes whereby to apply comfort or <note place="margin">SECT. 6.</note> the favour of God to themſelves, then they are driven preſently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> conſideration with themſelves, what the reaſon ſhould be that they may not enter into the Sanctuary, and touch the holy things; and why they may not feaſt with Chriſt at his <hi>Table</hi> as well as others? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 30.</note> and why their fellowſhip is ſhunned in ſuch exerciſes wherein wee draw neereſt unto God, and converſe familiarly with him? Why their ſeed may not bee baptiſed, nor themſelves accepted as the Lords gueſts, but are excluded from all ſuch things as may encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and comfort them, being, as it were, <hi>bound hand and foot,</hi> and may <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 12. 13. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 7. 10.</note> heare of nothing but of the <hi>Law,</hi> judgement and threatening againſt them: and in this, every mans heart ſhall anſwer him, and hee ſhall ſay; it is, becauſe I walke in fleſhly libertie, and give my ſelfe to vaine and evill courſes; I am a common ſwearer, a lyer, a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembler, a wanton, a drunkard, a griper after the world, or ſome ſuch evill, for which, as God hath ſaid, I ſhall not enter <hi>into his Kingdome;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 6 9.</note> ſo his people ſhun mee, and get them from mee, and had rather have my room than my company, I muſt know nothing of <hi>the Lords ſecrets,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. 14.</note> becauſe I feare him not, they will tel me nothing of their ſweet comforts, but I languiſh about temporarie toyes, and fleet up and downe as the world favours and frownes, and the height of all my comfort is, but to have my cattell, <hi>my corne,</hi> my trade and my wealth <hi>increaſe;</hi> or if theſe faile, to cheere up my heart with a cup of ſtrong <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. 7.</note> liquor, or to heare or ſee ſome Tragedie or merry conceit, and if theſe things helpe not mee. I am left remedileſſe; but I ſee there are others that can <hi>comfort</hi> themſelves <hi>in God,</hi> when the world failes them, and can <hi>rejoyce in tribulation,</hi> and mocke the world, as ſcorning to <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30. 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 3. <hi>Iob</hi> 1. 21.</note> have their hearts moved much with any ſuch tranſitory things.</p>
               <p>Now ſurely theſe men have found ſome extraordinary matter to reſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and ſtay themſelves in and if I were reformed, &amp; reſtrained from my evill life, and did become a new man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſhould know what it is, and they would be right glad of my fellowſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> embrace me and honour me as the Diſciples <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> I muſt even <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 22, 23.</note> goe onely with a few <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> idle
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119581:16"/> dreames, and walke up and downe as a thiefe with a halter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of God and his people, and if death ſeize on me in this eſtate, before I amend, as I am excluded from all fellowſhip of Chriſtians here, ſo ſhall I for ever be ſhut from them in the kingdome of glory, and if there be a hell, ſurely I ſhall fall into it.</p>
               <p>And this will worke repentance in many, and in others a reſtraint, and as for Atheiſts and Hypocrites, which are in <hi>league with hell,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 21. 14.</note> have ſought againſt the light of reaſon and conſcience, till they are <hi>paſt feeling</hi> they will hereat the more diſcover themſelves, and <hi>foame out</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 19. <hi>Iude.</hi> 1. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>their owne ſhame,</hi> that the faith, patience and ſincerity of the godly may the better appeare, and be approved, and the condemnation of the other the more juſt.</p>
               <p>Whereas contrariwiſe, when all manner of graceleſſe men are fed <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> with the ſeales and pledges of Gods fauour, and inveſted into the full <note place="margin">It hinders wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to give the Sacraments.</note> privilege and higheſt prerogative with the moſt godly in the Church, and that it is daily told him, <hi>there is the body and blood of Chriſt given for him,</hi> how preſumptuous doe they grow? and how confident of their owne excellency? how audacious in evill? and how <hi>ſcornefull</hi> againſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. 6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123. 4.</note> men of a ſtrict and ſober life? no reproofes nor counſell, nor exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can take effect with them, nor ſcarce have an eare lent it. Tell them of wicked men and damnation, they'll ſend you to <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Turkie</hi> or <hi>India,</hi> amongſt the Heathens or Papiſts, for why? they are Proteſtants, and have a ſound Religion, and are borne, baptized, and brought up in a Chriſtian common-wealth and Church, and <hi>eate the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn:</hi> 6. 53.</note> 
                  <hi>fleſh, and drinke the blood of Chriſt,</hi> in whom they ſay, they truſt to be ſaved; <hi>though they never imitate his examples,</hi> but notwithſtanding all <note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 6. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12. 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 23.</note> their preſumption, they have not ſtroke one true ſtroke at ſinne, nor begun the worke of mortification, nor crauled one foot from their corruptioins, much leſſe are they entered into the ſtate of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, or begun the life of grace, but doe make the Goſpel, and the ſeales thereof in the abuſe thereof, a cloake for their ſin and as a char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to beare them out in all their evills, like thoſe rebellious <hi>Iewes,</hi> who brought <hi>oblations</hi> and cryed, <hi>The Temple, The Temple,</hi> when their hands <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 7. 4. 8, 9. <hi>Iſay</hi> 1. 13.</note> were <hi>full of blood,</hi> and their wayes fraught with all wickedneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119581:17"/>
               <head>It is in vaine to ſeeke the reformation of a Church, when the materialls are naught.</head>
               <p>THe Church being a building or houſe, if it ſo fall out that the <note place="margin">SECT. 7.</note> maine pillars and materialls are rotten, and that it is founded but upon Briers, brambles and rubbiſh, how ſhall this houſe ever be mended or made ſound, otherwiſe then by a quite demoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the frame, and building another of other and ſounder ſtuffe?</p>
               <p>Many have ſought divers wayes to reforme and amend this Church, but all helpeth not, except the matter were more ſound and ſolid.</p>
               <p>Some cry out vehemently upon the <hi>Prelates</hi> and Governours of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Church, thinking, that if they were away, all would be well, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <note place="margin">The Biſhops in <hi>England</hi> better then the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall multitude of the Land.</note> how much they are deceived, appeares in this: firſt, The <hi>Prelates</hi> are not worſe, nor in any ſenſe ſo evill, comparatively, as the generall multitude is, either for ignorance, prophaneneſſe, inhumanity, &amp;c. ſo as there were ten times more reaſon to deſire to be freed from the generall multitude then from them: ſecondly, Neither is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to governe this rude and unbroken multitude by an Elderſhip, or <hi>Presbyteriall</hi> policie; for they would laugh them to ſcorne, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <note place="margin">Chriſtian El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders muſt have no carnall weapons.</note> they had ſecular power conferred upon them, or attending on them (which were the way to make every Pariſh a high Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) their counſell, admonitions, and cenſures, ſhould be in as baſe eſteeme as <hi>Lots</hi> counſell was among the <hi>Sodomites;</hi> ſo that the <hi>Prelates</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. 9.</note> government is the beſt that can be for ſuch a tumultuous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broken multitude.</p>
               <p>Others there are, that would faine cry downe the <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Cap, Surplice, Croſſe, kneeling, &amp;c.</hi> and perſwade themſelves, that if they might not be urged, all would be well. And moſt true it is, they are matters neither commendable nor uſefull, but might well be ſpared, without any danger that I know of, but what ſhall we ſay? they are <note place="margin">The ceremonies are fit orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall multitude.</note> ſuch ornaments and jewels, as this multitude and their forefathers brought with them out of <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſſe and they are ſtill good enough for a people, whoſe Religion ſtands more in formes and figures, then in truth and ſubſtance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and if there were no wiſer then <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 17. 33. 34</note> I, they ſhould keepe them ſtill, and be halfe Proteſtants halfe Papiſts, which is juſt neither<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> untill they had reformed their morall vices, which are againſt the cleare light both of Scripture and Reaſon, and as for the godly and right informed Chriſtians they ſhould in their Church eſtate, be farre enough from ſuch vaine aſſemblies or vaine ordinances.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119581:17"/>
               <p> Others there are, who thinke, that if every Pariſh might chooſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> their owne Miniſter, all would goe well, but theſe are but vaine ſuppoſitions without ground; For, firſt, if the Pariſhes had that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty <note place="margin">The Pariſh aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies not fit men to chooſe their Miniſters</note> freely given them, and that the body of the multitude might come together to caſt up their caps at ſuch an <hi>Election,</hi> there were like enough to be entertainment for all the looſe and idle Schollers and blacke Coats, that any of our well governed Schooles ſhould ſpew out, of which, though ſome now be entertained ſhamefully, yet then doubtleſſe many more would be, elſe how could there be like <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 24. 2. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 9. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 7.</note> people like Prieſt? ſecondly, What have ſuch men to doe, to give voyce or ſentence to chooſe or refuſe any man about the ſervice of God, who care not for God, neither know either him or them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? thirdly, with what comfort could any godly man ſtand Miniſter unto them, to whom in equall proportion (ſince they have choſen him) hee muſt proſtitute the holy things, whileſt they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine diſobedient and unfaithfull?</p>
               <p>Some others there are, who ſtumble at the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> Courts; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> others are offended at the forme and <hi>Ring in marriage;</hi> ſome are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about the <hi>croſſe;</hi> others at the <hi>ſurplice;</hi> ſome will not have their <note place="margin">The pariſh mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude worſe then any cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note> wives <hi>Churched;</hi> others will not <hi>kneele</hi> at the Sacrament, &amp;c. and ſo one in one thing, and another in another thing, even as they affect and have ſet their mindes, ſtumbling at a ſtraw, and leaping over a blocke, like <hi>Ionah,</hi> who was angry to death for the <hi>Goard,</hi> but the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ion.</hi> 4. 8. 9. 10. 11</note> death of a thouſand people never grieved him: or like little children which leave open the doores, that thieves may come in, and then cover them under the bed cloathes. Alas, what ſafety is there in amending theſe trifles, when the body is naught, and can brooke no perſon or thing that is good? were not he a fooliſh man, that having a rotten carkaſſe, ready to drop in pieces, would yet ſend for ſome furbuſhing Surgeon to take off the warts, and helpe the wrincles of his face; can any ſuch thing make an evill tree an evill man, or an evill multitude <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 20.</note> good? If all humane inventions were taken from them, and all Gods pure Ordinances executed among them, were they any thing the better; or were they not indeed ſo much the worſe, and the further in the guilt of taking <hi>Gods name in vaine?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore I conclude, it is a ſequeſtration, and not a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation that will heale us, helpe us, and give us a right Church eſtate for to joyne unto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119581:18"/>
               <head>It is a matter of great weight and neceſſity, for Chriſtians to live in a right ordered Church.</head>
               <p>BUt ſome, perhaps, may thinke it a ſmall matter, and a needleſſe <note place="margin">SECT. 8.</note> thing for a man to come into any other Church eſtate or order, but that in the midſt of theſe confuſions, he may content him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> to heare now and then ſome profitable <hi>Sermons</hi> in the aſſemblies, and catch here and there a piece, in reading, hearing and conferring, by which he may not onely become a true Convert, but alſo be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and ſtabliſhed in grace, and have his ſoule fed and nouriſhed to life eternall; and if ſalvation may be had in that eſtate, what need is there to come into any other Church order?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, that it is not denyed but it is poſſible that men may be <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> ſaved who never come into a right Church-eſtate and order, but knowing no better, or through weakneſſe fearing to doe better, live and die in this Church (or ſome worſer) as it is; for we doe not make the <hi>viſible Church</hi> to be ſo priviledged as that none out of it can be <hi>ſaved;</hi> for we receive men into the Church, whom we deeme faithfull, and in Chriſt before: And the right uſe of the <hi>Offices and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 41.</note> 
                  <hi>Ordinances</hi> in the Church are properly to build up, and keepe men in the faith and obedience of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> rather then to bring them to it; The Church is a ſpirituall corporation, wherein the ſubjects of the heavenly <hi>King</hi> are kept in a more comely order and better obedience, <note place="margin">Faith and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is not tyed to the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church.</note> but the <hi>incorporating</hi> or joyning to the Church doth not make men ſubjects of Chriſt, which before were not; but it is an ignorant va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to hold that unconverted men may be received into the Church and fellowſhip of the Saints, under hope of converting them. Wee therefore grant, that converſion, faith, grace and ſalvation, may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be had in many of theſe aſſemblies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea, we know many who have the true ſignes thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who yet live and converſe in them. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But what then? Will men uſe the utmoſt liberty they can, that they may alſo pleaſe the fleſh and the world, and avoid perſecution, if they may but be even thread-bare Chriſtians, and in the end be ſaved? ſurely I would not have any good man have ſuch a thought, ſince it is ſo neer of kin to <hi>hypocriſie;</hi> for even <hi>Hypocrites</hi> will ſerve God <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 6.</note> for wages, and would doe ſo much good as might bring them to <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> but ſincere and conſcionable Chriſtians uſe to have reſpect <hi>to all Gods Commandements,</hi> and to ſuch further degrees of obedience, as <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 33. and 19. 25, 26. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. 3. 4.</note> God from time to time ſhall <hi>reveale unto them;</hi> for otherwiſe their faith and obedience may of themſelves be queſtioned, whether it proceed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119581:18"/> from the <hi>love of God</hi> or themſelves, ſeeing they can doe nothing further then may barely pleaſure themſelves?</p>
               <p>And as God ſaw it <hi>not good for man</hi> in innocencie <hi>to be alone,</hi> and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> therefore ſanctified marriage for his mutuall helpe, ſo as he hath ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 18.</note> Saints <hi>out of the world</hi> by here and there a man, hee hath alſo ſanctified <hi>fellowſhips,</hi> and Churches, which muſt neither be deſpiſed <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 22. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10. 25.</note> nor <hi>forſaken;</hi> and this brotherly fellowſhip of the Church hath beene ſo longed after, and loved of Gods ſervants, as that they have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 1.</note> it to the moſt pleaſant dew and ſweet oyntment, the one ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133. 2. 3. <hi>Numb.</hi> 24. 5.</note> the eye, the other delighting the ſmell, yea, even <hi>Balaam</hi> that Sorcerer was content to commend the <hi>comely</hi> harmony and order of the <hi>Tents</hi> of the houſe of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and how excellent and pleaſant a thing it is, to ſee the Saints &amp; ſervants of God communicate together in his <note place="margin">The beautie of the viſible Church.</note> ſacred Ordinances, and how fruitfull and profitable ſuch courſes are, hath in part beene ſhewed already, and ſhall more fully hereafter. And I muſt out of mine owne experience confeſſe, that the living in a ſociety of Chriſtians ſet in the right order of the Goſpel, is one of the greateſt helpes we have in this world, to the obedience of the <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 12.</note> Goſpell, yea, and ſo full it is of ſweet and ſound comfort that it even raviſheth the <hi>Angels,</hi> and is indeed next to heaven it ſelfe, if things be carried with holineſſe, wiſedome and love.</p>
               <p>For in ſuch a Church all the gifts and graces of the ſpirit are freely <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſhewed forth without reſtraint, there the Word of God is not bound <note place="margin">The profit and ſweet comfort of the Church.</note> in by policy, tradition, cuſtome, &amp;c. the utmoſt extent of Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations to the ſonnes of men, are there openly diſplayed, and the higheſt ſtraine of pure affections are there ſhewed; if you have a <hi>word of wiſedome</hi> or <hi>exhortation,</hi> there you may utter it. If you would <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 29. 30, 31.</note> 
                  <hi>learne any thing,</hi> there you may aske and receive freely; If you have cauſe to weepe and mourne, they will mourne with you; or have you cauſe of joy? they'll rejoyce with you; ſtand you in need of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>exhortation or comfort?</hi> they are ready to give it you; doe you <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 3.</note> ſtumble or fall, either by error of judgement, or <hi>failing</hi> in converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? why, they will help both to raiſe and hold you up; have you <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 1.</note> need of ſome, <hi>gentle rebukes,</hi> as a balme to your ſoule; or of ſome ſharp <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141. 5.</note> and ſevere threatnings to beat downe your <hi>proud fleſh;</hi> yea, need you ought either for ſoule or body? why, there it is to be had <hi>freely;</hi> and whatſoever is wanting in the outward glory, is ſupplyed ſeven fold in the inward grace, yea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and I may ſay of it as <hi>Sabaes</hi> Queene ſaid of <hi>Salomons</hi> wiſdome, <hi>It was not told me the halfe;</hi> nor it cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9. 6.</note> either with pen or tongue, what wonderfull pleaſure and ſweetneſſe there is in a Chriſtian fellowſhip.</p>
               <p>And out of doubt, if wee were not fuller of carnall policie and ſenſuality then wee are of ſpirituall grace and ſoundneſſe, wee would rather chooſe to endure afflictions and <hi>death,</hi> in ſuch a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 25. 26.</note>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119581:19"/> then to live in the Courts of Kings, <hi>yoaked</hi> with infidels and evill livers.</p>
               <p>And if at the laſt day the righteous ſhall <hi>ſcarcely be ſaved,</hi> and that <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 18.</note> many ſhall goe ſo farre, as to preach Chriſt, and doe many great works <hi>in his Name,</hi> and yet ſhall be ſhut out of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> what <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note> great care had there need to be to ſearch and ſound our hearts and to uſe and improve all the helps and meanes which God hath left for our growth and ſtabliſhing in grace, and for provoking and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 13.</note> of us to proceed from one degree of perfection to another; and if men did but know how much it ſtood them in hand to regard and love the converſing in a right ordered Church, they would give their ſoules no reſt till they were in it; but for want of experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall knowledge thereof they dote upon their <hi>Syrian</hi> waters, as <hi>Naaman</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note> did upon <hi>Abanah,</hi> and <hi>Parphar;</hi> but if they had taſted the <hi>pleaſant</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eze.</hi> 47: 1. 2, 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtreames</hi> that flow from this <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> they would rather be doore-keepers therein then dwell in the tents of the ungodly.</p>
               <p>Yea and we ſee daily, that even the corruptions and frailties of men <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> do call for ſuch a meanes to help them forward; for ſuch is the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and perverſneſſe of our nature, as that we are apt to ſet light by the doctrine taught in the aſſemblies and think the Preacher ſpake to ſuch and ſuch, but it belongeth not to us, like <hi>David,</hi> who was in a <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 2. 3. 7</note> ſweet dreame, all the while that <hi>Nathan</hi> propounded his generall Parable, but when the <hi>Prophet</hi> told him that he was <hi>the man;</hi> he began to looke about him: ſo we have divers that have made ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe <note place="margin">The neceſſity of the diſcipline of Chriſt.</note> in <hi>Religion,</hi> and yet ſticke in ſome evill practice or other in converſation, and can ſmile upon the <hi>Preacher,</hi> and goe merrily home, thinking, becauſe he named them not, that he hath given them leave to goe on in evill, and ſo they doe, and there is no further meanes to pull them out.</p>
               <p>But in a ſociety of Chriſtians, under the policy of the Goſpel, the Word of God followeth them home to their doores, and in o their callings and converſations, yea, into their chambers and ſecret places, and the <hi>brother offended</hi> at their ſwarving from Chriſt, reproveth, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth, and perſwadeth to obedience, and if gentle admonitions will not prevaile, he uſeth ſharpneſſe; and if the ſinne be notorious and <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> and that the perſon will not humble himſelfe and repent, he proceedeth to open rebuke and cenſure thereof (as before is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) that if it be poſſible the offender may be recovered and ſaved, and if <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</note> not, yet that the fellowſhip may be purified and purged, and ſcandall removed from the profeſſors of the Goſpell and way of God.</p>
               <p>Beſides, the revolting and back-ſliding of many Chriſtians, even cryeth out for this help; many profeſſors of Religion are often drawn <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> aſide to baſe and ſervile uſe of this world, and often times grow <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, prodigall or wanton in fleſhly liberty,</hi> and in this doing, they have <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. 18.</note>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119581:19"/> many of their pariſh members to uphold and <hi>favour them,</hi> and what <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 31.</note> meanes uſe the Chriſtian profeſſors to recover ſuch? doe they any more then talke of it one to another; and ſay ſuch a one hath done this, and he hath done that, toſſing the evill about without feare, and <hi>glorying</hi> in their owne gifts, eminence and integrity, ſpeaking bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 2. 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> againſt them; but other meanes to recover the offender, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the ſcandall from the Goſpel, they have none, nor none they looke after, except ſome unadviſed man run and fetch a ſentence from ſome who had need to be firſt cenſured themſelves.</p>
               <p>Whereas, if they had the right uſe of diſcipline amongſt them, no doubt, thouſands of ſuch might be recovered, to the great joy of themſelves and others, whereas now, going on without this meanes, who can tell, whether ever they returne out of the ſnare of the Divell?</p>
               <p>And truely, even the moſt godly ſtand need oftentimes to be helped by particular rebukes and admonitions, and it is no ſmall priviledge for them to live in ſuch a ſociety, as where the eyes of their brethren are ſo lovingly ſet upon them, that they will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to goe on in ſinne; and though it often ſeeme <hi>grievous</hi> to our nature, to be <hi>rebuked,</hi> yet upon ſecond thoughts, and ſerious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation, they count themſelves happy men, that ever they lived in ſuch a ſociety, as would not <hi>ſuffer</hi> them to tranſgreſſe, yea, and though many Chriſtians be ſo mortified, that they cannot fall into any ſcandalous ſinne, yet their faults may be great in hiding their <hi>talents,</hi> and not improving their gifts and endowments for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, in which, though themſelves thinke all is well, and pleaſe themſelves in a kinde of modeſtie; yet others of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſee it to be a great fault in them, and give them no reſt till they have drawne them to ſet their light upon the <hi>Table.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what pitie is it to ſee ſo many gifts and graces of God to lie hid and aſleepe, for want of opportunity and provocation to uſe them? all which, if they were in a ſociety and Church of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and zealous men, would be brought forth, and made uſe of to the glory of God, the benefit of others, and the great comfort of ſuch as have and uſe theſe graces: And thus we ſee of what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie it is for all Chriſtians to joyne themſelves unto, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe in a ſociety of faithfull men, walking viſibly in the order of the Goſpel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:119581:20"/>
               <head>The reformed Churches are not condemned, but admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by this ſtrict practice.</head>
               <p>SOme object, that this Profeſſion and practice, in admitting no Religious fellowſhip with wicked men, condemneth all refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches in <hi>France, Belgia, Helvetia, &amp;c.</hi> ſince they are very defective in their people and companies for the moſt part.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, firſt, that theſe are but <hi>popular</hi> and needleſſe exceptions to make a noyſe in the world, and to bring us in the more contempt: ſecondly, the <hi>reformed Churches</hi> are not ſo well knowne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, as that we can paſſe any ſentence upon them, ſimply to juſtifie them or condemne them: thirdly, ſo farre as we doe know them, we finde them ſeparated and diſtinguiſhed from the vaine world, and ſo are not ours: fourthly, the things they doe in the <hi>worſhip</hi> of God are voluntary, and without <hi>compulſion,</hi> ſo are not ours: fifthly, their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers are choſen by the congregation, ſo are not ours: ſixthly, their worſhip is onely the Word of God, and the lively graces of his ſpirit; ſo is not ours: ſeventhly, their government is by an <hi>Elderſhip</hi> or <hi>Presbytery,</hi> ſo is not ours; And all theſe things ſorting together, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, we are farre from condemning them, and are farre neerer them in our practice, then the pariſh aſſemblies are.</p>
               <p>And if yet by reaſon of their great <hi>popularitie</hi> in ſome Cities, where divers thouſands are of one Church, (and ſo meete in ſundry ſeverall places) and ſo cannot poſſibly be knowne of their <hi>Officers,</hi> or of one another, but that many corrupt perſons may lurke amongſt them, and not be found out, and ſo <hi>ſcandall</hi> is brought upon them: ſecondly, or that by long cuſtome, and for feare of inconveniences, all private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes are uſed onely by their <hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>Officers:</hi> thirdly, or that for feare of ſome men, or through error of judgement they <hi>baptize</hi> the Infants of all manner of wicked parents, that are of no Church or Religion, being brought unto them; If I ſay for theſe and the like failings we reprove and exhort them, and deſire their amendment, and practice otherwiſe our ſelves, yet it doth not follow, nor is true, that we condemne them.</p>
               <p>Neither is a man bound to determine of other perſons then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for the certainty of their eſtate, nor of other Churches then that where he lives, for their externall obedience: firſt a man is bound to ſee that his owne eſtate be good with God; next, he is to looke to it, that he live in ſuch a Church and Society, where all the meanes and helps are to continue him in that eſtate; but for other perſons and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119581:20"/> Churches, all meddling with them ſhould be ſparing and modeſt, and except ſome <hi>preſumptuous evidences</hi> appeare, and that a man be juſtly called to ſhew his judgement, the leſſe he ſpeaketh of them, the more honeſty and wiſedome he declares.</p>
               <p>And were it ſo, that we ſhould condemne the <hi>reformed Churches,</hi> (which God forbid) and therein doe fooliſhly and raſhly, what were that to the juſtification of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> or for the hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our exceptions againſt it; except you will frame this conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that becauſe we are in one thing, therefore we are in all, which is too hard a ſentence to ſtand for a <hi>maxime.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither doe we ſay, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is <hi>no Church,</hi> or the pariſh aſſemblies, falſe Churches, nor care for thoſe big and loud cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Antichriſtian, Babyloniſh, falſe, &amp;c.</hi> they are but words and termes of provocation, which we can well ſpare; and it is enough that we finde it not ſettled according to the order of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> but by humane authority and compulſion, and that it is one with the world, and that there is not in it all the meanes to ſtabliſh, comfort confirme and build up every ſoule in the wayes of God: theſe and the like are ſufficient motives to perſwade men that feare God, to finde out a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſafer way to walke in, and a Church that is more neer the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> patterne.</p>
               <p>And as for ſtrangers, and Churches in forraign nations, as they are not of our language, ſo we cannot know them as our owne; for he that knoweth ſtrangers and forraigners, as well as his owne neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and country-men, it is a ſigne that he is very unſociable, or elſe his eyes are not where they ſhould be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The prohibition of the Magiſtrate, though he be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, may not hinder our obedience to the Goſpel.</head>
               <p>SOme object, and that not without colour, that ſince we live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrate,</hi> we muſt be contented, and thankfully accept ſo much liberty in the Goſpel as he will allow, and that it is a ſigne of great unthankfulneſſe and diſloyalty to him, to alter or adde in Church matters, and publique worſhip, or to doe more, or otherwiſe then he commandeth or alloweth.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, firſt, that when the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are Chriſtians, we are <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>1</label> the more to love and reſpect them for their Chriſtianity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but ſtill their <hi>Magiſtracie</hi> and civill <hi>power</hi> is one thing, and their Chriſtianity and Religion is another.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the ſame reverence and conſcionable obedience were <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119581:21"/> to be given to the civill power, as Gods Ordinance, though the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which hath this power, were a <hi>Turke,</hi> or an <hi>Infidell;</hi> but not the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. 2.</note> ſame love in the fellowſhip of the Goſpel and communion of grace.</p>
               <p>Neither doth the Scripture provide for any other kinde or meaſure <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of obedience to Chriſtian <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> (when any ſuch ſhould ariſe) then for ſuch as were <hi>Heathens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, neither can I ever conceive, how this ſhould become a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> reaſon, that we muſt forbeare theſe and theſe practices which God <note place="margin">Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands may not ſtand againſt Gods.</note> requireth, becauſe the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are Chriſtians, and forbid it, except it follow alſo, that we muſt alſo forbeare it if they were <hi>Heathens;</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a man ſhould hold this poſition, that a man is in more bondage under Chriſtian <hi>Governours,</hi> then under <hi>Heathens,</hi> ſince the queſtion is not concerning ſuffering, but concerning doing: and if any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Magiſtrate ſhall by any acts or lawes <hi>politicall,</hi> hinder the practice of Gods <hi>Lawes;</hi> as his Chriſtianity cannot excuſe him in the Court of heaven, for miſleading, ſo much leſſe can it excuſe us, when we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him in evill; and whatſoever the power be, or the perſon which hath it, if it fight againſt Gods <hi>Injunctions,</hi> we may anſwer with them <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 29.</note> that ſaid God is to be <hi>obeyed rather then man;</hi> and if we ſhould be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to <hi>pray</hi> or to <hi>preach,</hi> or <hi>to love brotherly fellowſhip, &amp;c.</hi> yet theſe <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 17. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. 7. 10.</note> things muſt ſtill be done in the moſt ample manner we can.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, neither is it any diſloyalty to Princes and Governours at <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> all, when Gods commands are preferred before theirs, eſpecially ſince we are willing to ſuffer their corrections and puniſhments for ſo doing, counting indeed; their corrrections, but as Flea-bites, to his which can caſt both body and ſoule into hell. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 28.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, and in the things wherein we muſt differ, we endeavour <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> to carry them peaceably, ſo farre as we can without diſturbing, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracing or depraving any offices or orders by him placed, not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying, but willingly hearing the Word from any conſcionable and faithfull Preacher,, and ſo farre as we may without ſinne, to ſubmit to other orders; being moderate in our affections, peaceable in our practices, in the things wherein we differ; and if all that ſerve not, we ſhall thinke it our further glory to ſuffer, and endure any puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, either to bands or death with patience, that we may fulfill our <note place="margin">Obedience to Magiſtrates may be in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering as well as in doing.</note> courſe with joy, and not be aſhamed of his baſeneſſe, who ſuffered a ſhamefull death to advance us to a glorious life: and we proteſt in the ſight of God, that we can make no other anſwer or excuſe from the Magiſtrates Chriſtianity, except wee ſhould flatter him, and deceive our ſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119581:21"/>
               <head>Moſes <hi>example in building the Tabernacle, was no ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary rule for after times.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MOſes</hi> the Man of God, a good Governor did appoint all things for the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> and publique ſervice of God, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting <note place="margin">SECT. 11.</note> either with Prieſt or people, and had the <hi>wrath of God</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>4</label> againſt any that oppoſed his courſes; ſo now the people and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 32. <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. 31. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. 2.</note> muſt have an eye to the godly <hi>Governours</hi> to ſee what they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and ſee that they practiſe it, without impoſing, infuſing or practiſing otherwiſe in any thing then he alloweth.</p>
               <p>I anſwer: firſt, this ſheweth what godly Magiſtrates are to doe <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> in the matters of Gods ſervice, namely, to obſerve his will; but what <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the <hi>Prieſts</hi> or people might have done, if <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould have beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, is yet queſtionable.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Moſes,</hi> as he was a Prince, ſo he was a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> onely <hi>Prophet</hi> that ever was, except Chriſt, and he had his familiar <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 34. 10.</note> talke with God, for all matters about the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and was by him <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. 11.</note> immediately directed; ſo that for any to go about to direct and order him in thoſe things, had been high preſumption and undoubted evill. But now, no <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> that I know of, are ſuch <hi>Prophets,</hi> or have <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſingular.</note> any ſuch immediate Revelations, but learne of God according to the common order of other men; yea, and ſtand in as much need of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and advice (that I ſay not more) as any other men of any calling whatſoever; and therefore till they have <hi>Moſes</hi> learning, how ſhall they uſe <hi>Moſes</hi> teaching?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, neither did the Princes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> afterward take upon them this ſole direction, but were contented to be reproved and counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> by the <hi>Prophets</hi> &amp; <hi>Prieſts,</hi> both for their failings in their converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and for their eſtabliſhing the worſhip of God, as we may ſee in <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17. 4. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. 2. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 11. 17. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. 23. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>David, Aſa, Iehoſaphat, Ioaſh, Ioſiah,</hi> and the reſt, yea, and all the writings of <hi>Iſaiah, Ieremy, Ezechiel,</hi> and the reſt, are ſo many ſermons of direction and advice to the <hi>Kings of Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iuda:</hi> Now, if theſe godly Kings did thus, who can thinke that any now can be privileged ſo farre as to be ſole Law-givers for the Church of God?</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the Revelations of <hi>Moſes</hi> were delivered with ſuch <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Majeſty, Signes, Miracles</hi> and <hi>wonders</hi> from heaven as no man could <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 18. and 40. 38. &amp; 24. 8.</note> doubt or call in queſtion, of the immediate finger of God, in the eſtabliſhing of them; but never ſince, nor now neither, are there any Laws or Precepts of Princes confirmed with that heavenly <hi>Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> but that doubt may be made, whether the King of heaven ratifie them or not?</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:119581:22"/>
               <p> Fifthly, When <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote Lawes, no man had ever written any <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> before him, ſo that as theſe Lawes were infallible, ſo they were alone, but now divers <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> make their Laws different, for the Church and Religion, and if we may not amidſt them all, and without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement to any man, cleave unto the Lawes of Chriſt, who infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly hath given the Lawes for the Church as did <hi>Moſes</hi> for the <hi>Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 1. 2. 5.</note> and is become our everlaſting <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Prophet</hi> for ever, and muſt reigne over his alone; we ſhall preſently have as many formes of Churches, as there ariſe Governours, and as many Church Lawes as the unſettled mindes, and uncertaine capacity of fraile man pleaſeth to make.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, If <hi>Moſes</hi> example in giving the Law for the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> teach us to ſubmit to the Religious Lawes of Chriſtian Princes now, without queſtioning or altering, then why ought we not alſo (if we live under them) to ſubmit to the <hi>Lutheran Arian,</hi> or <hi>Popiſh</hi> Princes? for it cannot be denyed, but that they are <hi>Chriſtians?</hi> And what folly and ignorance was it in the Martyrs aforetime to loſe their lives <note place="margin">A diſhonour to Martyrdome.</note> ſo many of them, and expoſe themſelves and theirs to ſuch ſlavery and miſery, if in the Court of heaven, and before God, they might have beene excuſed, ſo long as they had followed the Lawes of their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Governours?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The examples of the Kings of Iſrael and Judah, in reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Gods Worſhip, doe not bind to any faſhions in Religion, but Chriſts.</head>
               <p>IT is further objected from the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> as <hi>David,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">SECT. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Aſa, Hezechiah</hi> and <hi>Ioſiah, &amp;c.</hi> who reſtored Religion, repaired the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>5</label> Temple, and brought in the Law and the Ordinances without <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30. 1. &amp; 35. 1. 2, 3. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8. 1.</note> any advice or conſultation of the people; and ſo now, the Kings as agents to appoint and command the people as patients to ſuffer and obey that which is commanded, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, firſt, all this ſtill ſheweth what forwardneſſe there <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>1</label> ought to be in godly Princes when faithfulneſſe is departed from their Lands, namely, by their examples and edicts, to ſeeke to raiſe ſome life againe in that which is dead, but that the people may doe nothing in Gods worſhip, till their Princes begin, but may remaine as cold and as careleſſe, or ſuperſtitious as they, and as the rebellious Jewes were, is an unreaſonable and unſound affirmation.</p>
               <p>For it cannot be imagined but it had beene lawfull to have <hi>read</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> though <hi>Ioſiah</hi> had not commanded it; as alſo the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119581:22"/> Prieſts might have cleanſed the <hi>Temple,</hi> and have offered the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and the people might have eaten the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> and brought their oblations, though the Princes had forbid it, ſince theſe <hi>Statutes</hi> were <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 24. 25, &amp; 27. 21.</note> nor given onely to the <hi>Kings,</hi> but to all the <hi>Houſe of Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah</hi> were types of Chriſt, the eternall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> King, ſo they were ſucceſſors and imitators of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and they onely which moſt ſtrictly followed <hi>Moſes,</hi> are moſt approved and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for their <hi>faithfulneſſe;</hi> but now the ſucceſſion of <hi>Moſes</hi> being <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 23. 25.</note> cut off by a more perfect and better Lawgiver, there is now no Law or policie that can be deviſed for the gathering and ordering of the Church that deſerves any commendation, but onely Chriſts, yea, and whoſoever is not with Chriſt therein, is againſt him, and be he what he will, he is rather a ſcatterer than a gatherer with him.</p>
               <p>So that as the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> looked into the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to build, repaire and ſtabliſh the Temple and Ordinances of God, then; ſo now, if Princes will eſtabliſh Religion, and ſettle a Church, whither ſhall they goe for a patterne but to Chriſt?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A Compariſon of the patterne of Chriſts Church with the Church of England.</head>
               <p>CHriſt, though he had all power in heaven and earth, yet, he <note place="margin">SECT. 13.</note> raiſed no forces nor pitched no fields to compell Nations and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Countries to be of his Church, but ſent out his <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 18, 19. <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 17, 18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 4. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 20. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 34.</note> and <hi>Meſſengers</hi> unarmed in any <hi>carnall weapons,</hi> to paſſe thorow King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Countries, with intreatings and beſeechings, to gather here and there a man to him, and ſuch as by preaching would believe and by voluntary ſubmiſſion would obey, of them onely he became the <hi>Captaine</hi> and <hi>Head:</hi> ſecondly, when hee had gathered his Church together, he fed them not with dead decrees, nor carnall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 51. 53 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2.</note> but with his <hi>Word, Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> which nouriſhed to <hi>life eternall:</hi> thirdly, hee governed them not by any ſtately or pompous power, but by ſuch <hi>rules</hi> and regiments as their neceſſities required, and themſelves deſired. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And if now by glittering ſwords and ſounds of trumpets, Churches be gathered by thouſands, <hi>and that</hi> wee are growne to ſuch pomp and ſwelling in words, that we can talke of a <hi>Catholique</hi> viſible Church of <hi>a Chriſtian world,</hi> of a <hi>Nationall Church, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the multitudes ſound as loud as they will, I feare mee heaven will have never the more of them, but when all is done, his Word will ſtand that ſaith, <hi>Few finde</hi> the way to life, and Chriſt chooſeth not <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 13. 14.</note> a world, but a remnant out of the world.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:119581:23"/>
               <p> And yet, whileſt proud fleſh and carnall policie thus vainly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth how doe men ſtruggle and ſtrive by wit, policie and learning, to make that ſtand for truth, which onely times have hatched, and to make true Religion ſtand with all the faire ſhew in the fleſh that may be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but in the meane time, what <hi>ſcattering,</hi> ſcambling and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting there is, and how men are plunged and fumbled to bind the truth and the times in a bundell, that even the moſt wiſeſt and ableſt have even loſt themſelves about it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A proportionable application of the Iewes State, unto our times.</head>
               <p>TRue it is, that when the Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> commanded the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances <note place="margin">SECT. 14.</note> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the people were bound to obey them even in Religious rites, but if they ſhould have varied from <hi>Moſes</hi> rule, the queſtion is, whether the people might have followed them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne, though even <hi>David</hi> or <hi>Ioſiah</hi> ſhould have done it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, as for example, whereas <hi>Moſes</hi> gave his Statutes to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> if <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> now <hi>David</hi> ſhould have compelled the <hi>Edomites</hi> or the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> or the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> whom he conquered, to have come into the Temple, with offerings and oblations, being <hi>Gentiles</hi> and uncircumciſed; whether the <hi>Prieſts</hi> might have offered their offerings, and the people have prayed for a bleſſing or not?</p>
               <p>Secondly, if he would have made <hi>Prieſts</hi> of any other thcu of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> houſe of <hi>Aaron;</hi> whether the people might have brought their offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to them or not?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, if other matters then <hi>Moſes</hi> Law had ordinarily beene <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> read and preached in their <hi>Synagogues;</hi> whether the people muſt have come to heare it or not.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, if among the <hi>Iudicials</hi> hanging had beene uſed in ſtead of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> reſtitution, burning in ſtead of whipping, and cutting off the head in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. 1. <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 18. &amp; 25. 9.</note> ſtead of pulling off the ſhoe; whether the people muſt ſtill have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted accordingly.</p>
               <p>Firſt, But our aſſemblies are compact in a manner of blacke <hi>Ethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opians,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> prophane and inſulting <hi>Edomites,</hi> mocking and deriding <hi>Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, our Prieſts are made by an invented forme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and muſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> hang upon the univerſall race, and not by the lineall ſucceſſion of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 23.</note> grace, and therefore election of the people.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, and wee have other teaching and ſervice than the <hi>Word</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>and Spirit of Chriſt,</hi> viz. by <hi>Hom. Canons Apocrypha</hi> prayers &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119581:23"/>
               <p> Fourthly, and in ſtead of a Chriſtian conviction and cenſure of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> offenders by the Chriſtian aſſemblie, wee have <hi>Comminations</hi> read in <hi>Lent,</hi> and proceſſe comming out of Courts, which are bought and ſold, and flie in and out according to the purſe rather then according to the offence; and what ſhall we make of all this, if we put it toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſurely wee may compare it to a <hi>leprous</hi> body, in a painted paper coat, which neither hath ſoundneſſe within, nor ſolidneſſe without.</p>
               <p>But here is the queſtion, whether the godly muſt contentedly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to all this <hi>patcherie,</hi> and putting out that light, and diſcerning that they have in theſe things, may bleſſe their ſoules, and ſay it is onely the fault of our <hi>Governours?</hi> or whether all Chriſtians are not bound to keepe the patterne left by him who was more faithfull then <hi>Moſes,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 13.</note> without regarding what any Prince or Potentate doth to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Indeed whatſoever abuſe or neglect there had beene of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  <hi>Temple</hi> in Ieruſalem, by the Kings, yet the people might not without ſpeciall command have built another, but that <hi>Legall</hi> reſtraint was not by occaſion of any Kings command, but by a Statute of the Lord, who onely there had put his Name, and for a time it might not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; but now ſince mount <hi>zion</hi> is every where, and that God is no <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 11. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8. 29.</note> reſpecter of places or perſons but is in the middeſt <hi>of two or three</hi> of his ſervants, gathered in his Name, I ſee not how the Church in any ſenſe can be bound or tyed to the pleaſure and libertie of any mortall man whatſoever.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, and if <hi>Vzziah,</hi> being a godly <hi>King,</hi> was not onely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> when he would have <hi>burned Incenſe,</hi> but even thruſt out of the <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26. 18. 19. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Temple</hi> when once he became a <hi>Leper.</hi> And ſince ſinne was typed out by <hi>Leprouſie,</hi> and is ſo much more materiall then it, as a ſubſtance is of more value then a ſhadow; I ſee not, but if wicked rulers now ſhould offer to joyne to the Church, they may be refuſed, and then how much eaſier may ſuch Subjects and ſervants of theirs be refuſed, as are wicked and nought on whom the <hi>Leprouſie</hi> of all viciouſneſſe cleareth and ſheweth it ſelfe in the behaviour, countenance, words and actions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> notwithſtanding their owne deſire, and the deſire of any friends that love them not aright.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119581:24"/>
               <head>The ſubmiſſion of the Jewes to the Heathen Kings about building the Temple, is no imitable practice about the Church.</head>
               <p>SOme others object the example of the <hi>Heathen kings,</hi> as <hi>Cyrus</hi> and <note place="margin">SECT. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Darius,</hi> without whoſe leave the <hi>Iewes</hi> could not build the <hi>Temple,</hi> and therefore how much leſſe may we that are under Chriſtian <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>6</label> Princes, gather and eſtabliſh Churches without their direction or allowance?</p>
               <p>I anſwer firſt, That the time of building the <hi>Temple</hi> according to <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> the <hi>Prophets</hi> predictions was not come before they ſet about it; for if it had, they muſt have gone about it to their powers ſo ſoone as the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. 1. 2.</note> commandement had beene forth.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The building of the <hi>Temple</hi> was a matter of great charge <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and labour, and required ſuch materialls to doe it, as they being poore <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nehe.</hi> 2. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Captives,</hi> neither had, nor were able to accompliſh, ſo that there was an impoſſibility in it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they were ſervants, yea, captives and priſoners to thoſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>heathen Kings,</hi> and muſt not without a ſpeciall diſpenſation from God, (as was that of robbing the <hi>Egyptians)</hi> have left their Maſters <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 12 35. 36</note> and places, under whom by Gods juſt order they were captivated.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, It came of the Lord, that thoſe <hi>heathen Kings</hi> ſhould (after they had for a time corrected his people) become their friends and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> furtherers, in the ſervice of the Lord, turning their love into hatred, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nehe.</hi> 2. 4.</note> and at Gods appointed time, provoke and ſtrengthen them in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the houſe of the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and theſe things conſidered, what force can there be in this example?</p>
               <p>Fifthly, And how commeth this farre fetched type, to be ſo blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> urged, when the cleare truth in this point hath followed us ſo cloſe at the heeles? Did Chriſt when hee gave his Diſciples commiſſion to goe make Diſciples in all Nations, bid them firſt aske leave of the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> which were in thoſe parts? No ſurely, neither did the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19. 20.</note> Apoſtles and ſervants of Chriſt, when they went to and fro preaching the Goſpell, and ſtabliſhing Churches in <hi>Samaria, Phenice, Antiochia,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 5. and 11. 19. &amp; 18. 1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Corinth, Galatia, Crete,</hi> and the reſt, ever ſo much as aske leave of any of the heathen Governours to publiſh and ſtabliſh the Goſpell there?</p>
               <p>Sixthly, And if the allarme of the Goſpell muſt firſt be ſounded <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> in Princes Courts, and that the Kingdome of Heaven muſt come with ſuch <hi>obſervations,</hi> we may ſometimes wait long enough, ſince the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 17. 20.</note>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119581:24"/> Goſpell, the ſubject wherereof is ſalvation, by a poore abject <hi>Carpenter,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marke.</hi> 6. 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 26. 28.</note> is too baſe a matter ever to be ſet by in ſuch places for the moſt part, otherwiſe then ſome parcells thereof may be received, ſo farre as it may procure outward ſafetie and glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The only way to eſtabliſh the Goſpel and the pure Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereof is to ſuffer perſecution for it.</head>
               <p>BUt now, ſeeing this age will goe no further than they are, nor <note place="margin">SECT. 16.</note> endure no other courſes in religion than that which is by Law eſtabliſhed, how ſhall wee doe? Muſt wee ſpend our money, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>7</label> and be diſturbed in our Calling? Muſt wee alter our diet, abate our habits, and change our lodgings? Alas, muſt we goe to priſon and lie there? O! that I would be loth to doe; many lie there and are poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned by the ill ayre and uſage, and beſides one knoweth not whether they will hang one or not, they are ſo violent and mercileſſe to all oppoſites, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, Doe not thouſands die in their beds of Feavers, Fluxes, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> Surfets, &amp;c. And can a man give his life for a better thing then for the honour of Chriſt, and be ſarcificed for the <hi>redeeming</hi> and recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that liberty of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> which this age refuſeth to heare of, and which fighteth againſt the confuſions and corruptions of our times? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> O that ſome Chriſtians rightly informed in theſe things would ſtand forth and ſuffer, and would not be delivered, but would rather die, then live to ſee Gods Ordinances ſo baſely contemned and thruſt out of place, and humane traditions upheld with ſtrong hand.</p>
               <p>Secondly, who ſeeth not that for want of <hi>reſiſting unto blood,</hi> all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and beginnings, which men have made, have come to little, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 4.</note> many have ſet on upon a purer practice, in divers places and ſo long as things could be carryed ſecretly, they went well on; but aſſoone <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 7.</note> as it began to be noted and talked againſt. Some would flie off pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently. And if they were once called in queſtion by authoritie, and threatned, there was preſently a ſcattering; and if ſome two or three were more ſtout then the reſt, then to priſon a while they were ſent; and then their friends and acquaintance would reſort to them; ſome with compaſſionate complaints, others with bigge ſpeeches, but all in carnall reaſons, till at laſt ſome mincing under hand acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">There muſt be no yeelding in the cauſe of Chriſt.</note> or ſome <hi>equivocating</hi> Proteſtation muſt be framed and ſhewed to their oppoſites<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo they ſhould get out with great charge to take heed of factions, <hi>ſchiſmes</hi> and <hi>conventicles;</hi> and ſo there lies the life and ſoule of that begun practice, and the parties afterward ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther become conformable, or elſe keepe themſelves very cloſe.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119581:25"/>
               <p> And what conſtruction can be made of this, but that either it was not truth they ſtood for, or that they were not rightly informed in it: but fell lightly and wantonly upon it, and ſo left it as lightly againe; or elſe that they made not conſcience of doing the will of God in the things revealed to them: whereas, if they had ſtoutly ſtood out, and borne their croſſe with patience even to bands and death; ſome other <note place="margin">The day of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for Chriſt is a day of honour.</note> events would have followed, and beſides their pretious &amp; honourable death, they ſhould have given ſome furtherance to the glory and truth of God, whereas by their cowardly yeelding, the arme of fleſh exulteth, and reproach and ſcandall is caſt upon the ſincere profeſſion and practice of Gods Ordinances, and themſelves commonly lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh for loſing the day, and are as men liveleſſe amongſt their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and comfortleſſe within themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The time of ſuffering is now come.</head>
               <p>ANd ſuch is the carnality of our times, even of the profeſſors of Religion, that they are never weary of eaſe, pleaſure and <note place="margin">SECT. 17.</note> plentie, nor feare the taking of too much <hi>thought for the fleſh,</hi> neither will they ever have the time come for judgement to begin <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 14.</note> at Gods Houſe, much leſſe with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> will they take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in <hi>afflictions and perſecutions;</hi> belike we are borne in the time when men muſt <hi>die in their neſts,</hi> and goe to heaven in <hi>feather-beds;</hi> and the <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 10. <hi>Iob</hi> 29. 18.</note> gate to heaven is growne ſo wide, that men may runne in at it with all invented formality and fleſhly libertie that can be invented or deſired.</p>
               <p>Some there are, who will pray earneſtly, that the abuſes in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Church may be removed, and the cleare light of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> really diſcovered, and that the Saints may rejoyce together in the ſweet fellowſhip of the Church, and it is well they doe ſo; but in their prayers they looke the wrong way for it ever to come in, they looke it ſhould be done with ſound of Trumpet, by decrees of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 18. 36.</note> by <hi>Edicts</hi> of Princes; alas, the Kingdome of Chriſt is not of this world, he gaines his glory here, by abaſement, and they that will doe any good in his cauſe, muſt caſt away all carnall helps<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth know Chriſt <hi>according to the fleſh no more,</hi> but walke cloſe with <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 16.</note> him in his temptation.</p>
               <p>And what doctrine is there in the Scriptures more cleare than this? Did not Chriſt himſelfe by death vanquiſh ſinne and Satan, <note place="margin">3. <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 26.</note> and ſo enter into glory? and was his whole life here any other then a continuall ſuffering? and were not theſe his ſufferings as well imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119581:25"/> as meritorious? Are not we to looke unto him who is <hi>the Authour and finiſher of our Faith,</hi> and follow him in his <hi>temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and are not all his promiſes made with the condition of the croſſe? Did not <hi>Paul</hi> deſire to have fellowſhip with Chriſt in his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marke</hi> 10. 30. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 10.</note> afflictions, and to be made conformable to his death? Well, how commeth it to paſſe, that wee never examine our ſelves by theſe things? nor thinke of ſuffering afflictions, but imagine that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pace and prevailing courſe of the times and multitude will ſerve the turne to bring us to glory? What priviledge have we above Chriſt, above <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Chriſtians in the Primitive time? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like no <hi>Prophet</hi> nor good man can periſh, or be wronged in our <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 13. 33.</note> Nation; but we are borne in the day, in which he that is moſt godly is the moſt ſecure.</p>
               <p>Well, if it be not ſo, I would it were ſo, but it is rather to be feared we joyne too much carnall libertie with our Profeſſion, and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> too eagerly deſire to make a faire <hi>ſhew in the fleſh,</hi> and meaſure Gods favour too much by temporall bleſſings; and we thinke, becauſe we build us faire houſes, and make us coſtly apparell, and eate our <note place="margin">A vaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit.</note> meate merrily, and lie and turne upon our feather-beds, with our braines full of roving thoughts, and traine up our children accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the faſhion, if withall we lend our eares ſometimes to a Sermon, and conferre ſometimes curſarily of the Scripture, and ſometimes uſe a forme of Prayer in our Families; we thinke God is wonderfully beholden to us, and we are ſome rare inſtruments of his glory, and notable <hi>pillars</hi> in his Church; for we ſit faſt and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 24.</note> quiet, and are not moved with errors, nor <hi>ſchiſmes;</hi> but when other <hi>buſie and giddie headed</hi> men that can never be quiet, rove and range about, troubled in minde, and diſtempered in affections, and fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pulling trouble upon themſelves, and beggery upon their wives and children; we live at wealth and peace and die quietly in our beds, and are honourably buried amongſt our friends, and leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde us a <hi>paterne</hi> and <hi>patrimony</hi> to our children.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Other motives to perſwadeus to ſuffering.</head>
               <p>BUt ſurely, if we had that zeale for the glory and houſe of God <note place="margin">SECT. 18.</note> which <hi>David</hi> had, wee would not dwell in our <hi>ſeeled houſes,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132. 2, 3.</note> nor give our ſelves to <hi>ſleepe and ſlumber,</hi> and ſee the houſe of the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hag.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4.</note> Lord lie waſte, and <hi>the ſtones thus ſcattered amongſt the rubbiſh,</hi> which <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102. 13, 14.</note> muſt not now be underſtood of any materiall <hi>Temple,</hi> but of the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall</hi> building of thoſe <hi>lively ſtones,</hi> the ſoules and bodies of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5.</note> into an <hi>holy Temple in the Lord;</hi> And this holy Temple lyeth yet
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119581:26"/> waſt, and the ſtones hid in the duſt and dung of the earth; And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 21. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 12.</note> the Lords time be come to delight in the fellowſhip of his Saints, and the <hi>Angels</hi> ſtand ready to rejoyce in the beautie of this Houſe, and Chriſt deſireth to walke amidſt the <hi>Candleſticks,</hi> and to take <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 1.</note> his repaſt <hi>with his beloved at noone.</hi> And yet here's all aſleep; and taking care for their wives, children, cattell, farmes and merchandize<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caut.</hi> 1. 6.</note> and they cannot come to this <hi>Supper</hi> of the Lord, to which they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 18, 19.</note> for feare of loſing ſome worldly toyes and trifles.</p>
               <p>Some will not truſt their owne judgements, others will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll their betters; ſome are right in judgement<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but are too cold and drouſie to come to action: others are fearefull and timerous, ſome runne lightly and fooliſhly without their errant, others are ſo wiſe, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 22.</note> that they can doe nothing. And thus by all and all, there is not that done that ſhould be: many labour to hew, poliſh and prepare ſtones, and timber for the building, but there is no ſound frame yet reared, or right forme appearing.</p>
               <p>And it were well if yet <hi>at the laſt houre of the day</hi> we could ſet our ſelves to this worke, and bring our ſoules and bodies into this <hi>holy houſe,</hi> in which a <hi>dayes</hi> dwelling were better then a <hi>thouſand</hi> elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. 10.</note> and truely, if wee had but tried the excellencie of this houſe, wee would thinke nothing too deare for it. And what if it ſhould coſt us our precious lives? can we beſtow them upon better termes? can wee live ever? or can we paſſe the time that God hath <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 13.</note> ſet? will not death as well finde us in our beds, as in the <hi>Iaole,</hi> or at <hi>Tiburne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And who can tell, whether we by carrying our ſelves humbly, modeſtly, and conſcionably before God and men, without depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving or abuſing them in authority, may not cauſe our <hi>haters</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. 45.</note> our <hi>lovers,</hi> and our enemies our friends, when our <hi>righteouſneſſe is brought forth as the light, and the judgement as the bright ſhining noone,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 6.</note> yea, if it be beſt for his glory, we are ſure he will deliver us from the oppreſſions of men and <hi>ſtrife of tongues,</hi> prolonging our dayes, and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 17. 18. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66. 12.</note> honouring us with <hi>gray hayres,</hi> as a <hi>Crowne of glory,</hi> being found in the <hi>way of righteouſneſſe,</hi> notwithſtanding all the oppoſitions of the times <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. 31.</note> and violence of men. <hi>But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t if he will not, but ſay he hath no pleaſure in us,</hi> nor that we ſhall not ſee the glory of his houſe, but ſhall die in <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 26.</note> the very endeavouring of it, <hi>let him doe what he pleaſe;</hi> and let it be enough, if our children may <hi>build this houſe,</hi> and enjoy the fruit of that which our lives payed for.</p>
               <p>And if wee muſt honour God with our bloods; let us doe it <note place="margin">Our lives are not too good to be given for Gods truth. <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 41. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 16.</note> cheerefully, rejoycing that we are found <hi>worthy to ſuffer for his name</hi> and let us caſt off this nice fleſh, and idle vanitie, conſult no more with <hi>fleſh and blood,</hi> but forſake our ſelves in that kinde, and if we will talke of heaven, let us contemne the earth, and be content <hi>to loſe lands,</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119581:26"/> 
                  <hi>goods and life</hi> for Chriſt and his Goſpels ſake; for elſe in looking after <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 8. 38.</note> heaven, we doe like the <hi>ſluggard which luſteth, but hath nought;</hi> and as children which gape for all their parents wealth, but will take no <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. 4.</note> paines to pleaſe them.</p>
               <p>Away with this ſelfe-love, that will have heaven and earth too, where is our love to Chriſt, that purchaſed heaven, ſince we will not <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 8. 36.</note> part with one dram of eaſe, pleaſure or profit for the furtherance of his <hi>Goſpel?</hi> And how can we be ſaid to honour him that will rather ceaſe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 20, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> our obedience to him in the things he requireth then part with a few worldly toyes and trifles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>It is no ſtrange thing for Chriſtians to be perſecuted of Chriſtians.</head>
               <p>BUt this is a very grievous thing, when a man ſhall not onely be <note place="margin">SECT. 19.</note> oppoſed and cruelly dealt withall at the hands of ignorant and <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>8</label> 
                  <hi>vaine men,</hi> but when many wiſe, <hi>Religious</hi> and godly men ſhall ſet themſelves againſt one, and be inſtruments of ones ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction? Me thinketh it cannot be, that ſuch good men ſhould be deceived and miſled as they are if I be right?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, firſt, Did not good <hi>Aſa</hi> put faithfull <hi>Hanant</hi> in priſon? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>1</label> Did not godly <hi>David</hi> diſpoſſeſſe true hearted <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> of his lands? <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 16. 10. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 4. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24. 23. <hi>Gen.</hi> 37. 28. <hi>Iob.</hi> 19. 2. 5.</note> Did not reforming <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> cauſe zealous <hi>zachariah</hi> to be ſtoned? Did not <hi>Ioſephs</hi> fellow <hi>Patriarches</hi> ſell him into <hi>Egypt?</hi> Did not <hi>Iobs</hi> wife and godly friends, vex and torment his ſoule more than all his other croſſes? Was not the holy <hi>Saint</hi> of God, <hi>Paul,</hi> deſpiſed and derided, even of his ſpirituall ſonnes? yea, ſometimes <hi>Manaſſes</hi> eateth <hi>Ephraim,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3. 10. 15.</note> and <hi>Ephraim Manaſſes,</hi> and therefore it is no ſtrange thing, to ſee one <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9. 20. 21.</note> Chriſtian abuſed, reviled, &amp; cruelly handled at the hands of another.</p>
               <p>Yea, and if it were ever in any age, it muſt needs be in ours, ſince greater ſtrictneſſe and cenſoriouſneſſe was never found againſt one <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> another, then is now, and no oppoſition or contrary opinion can be endured, but there muſt be a uniformity, even to the ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>mint and annis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if men be not borne all in one day, and brought up all in one Schoole, or enured to one Preacher, or that one man have learned a little faſter or ſlower then his fellowes, and begin to ſpeake either more plainly, or more darkely than ordinary, he is by and by diſtaſted and talked with, to ſee if he be not ſome <hi>Arian, Anabaptiſt, Familiſt, Browniſt, Puritane, &amp;c.</hi> and if any one of his allegations looke towards <note place="margin">The image of our times.</note> any of theſe Sects (as it were marvell if ſome ſhould not) then the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119581:27"/> hath ſomewhat to buſie himſelfe and his friends about, and there is a rare piece of worke done, an infected ſheepe diſcovered, and now he muſt be worried, and hunted, and where ſhall the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments be had to chaſe this creature? not from the rules of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity or logicke, except once or ſo, for recreation; but the weapons muſt be fetched out of the <hi>Cutlers ſhop</hi> that muſt cut the throat of thoſe errors, ad bring this <hi>Irregular</hi> fellow to a <hi>non plus,</hi> and the next newes <note place="margin">A notable wca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon to repreſſe errors.</note> he hears there is a <hi>purſevant</hi> at his back to carry him before authority, but when he comes there, ſome informers, (richer in clothes than in grace) have beene before him, and told his tale for him, ſo as there is nothing for him to ſay, except he will <hi>ſweare</hi> hee knowes not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and make anſwer hee knowes not to what, and after ſhort worke the man with the <hi>keyes</hi> muſt become his Hoſt, and with him he muſt eat hard meat, till either his withered Carkaſſe fall in the duſt, or be drawne upon a hurdle to <hi>Tiburne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus hath many a worthy Chriſtian been ſerved, and brought <note place="margin">Many good Chriſtians a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, and loſe their lives for trifles.</note> to his end, and what ſound and <hi>zealous</hi> Chriſtian is there more, which can ſay he is ſure he ſhall not be ſo ſerved? For though the things they hold have a good ground, and an honeſt intent, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences are rather about <hi>formes</hi> of words, than matters of weight; yet we live in ſuch a ſtrict and zealous age as will have a conformity, even betwixt the tips of mens tongues, and amongſt ſuch notable wiſe men, that can ſpy a fault where there is none.</p>
               <p>It is reported of Biſhop <hi>Grindall,</hi> that though his love to honeſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and zealous Preachers was ſuch as that for favouring of them, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Grindal.</hi>
                  </note> was ſuſpended from his <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> before his death; yet even in the middeſt of this his large love and lenity, by the inſtigation, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtallings of ſome <hi>Paraſites</hi> &amp; idle bellied <hi>Prieſts;</hi> he put to ſilence, one of <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Strood.</hi>
                  </note> the moſt famous &amp; worthieſt Preachers that ever was in that Dioces.</p>
               <p>I have alſo heard of a very excellent Preacher in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who was both a lover of goodneſſe and good men, and yet (partly by his <note place="margin">Maſter <hi>T. W.</hi>
                  </note> owne miſtaking, partly by others provocation) hee perſecuted an honeſt <hi>religious man,</hi> and one of his Pariſh, cauſing him to be put from his office which he had in the <hi>City,</hi> then to be deprived of worke <note place="margin">G. G.</note> or any reliefe from honeſt men, afterwards cauſed him to be <hi>impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned,</hi> where he lay above a yeere, till himſelfe, his wife and children were almoſt ſtarved; and had ſtarved but for ſome ſecret courſe, by <note place="margin">A lamentable example.</note> which they were relieved, and afterward comming out of priſon, he cauſed him to be baniſhed the <hi>City,</hi> and often threatned him with <hi>fire and faggot,</hi> and all for a triviall controverſie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein there was ten times more heat of blood than weight of difference.</p>
               <p>And untill our Preachers and Profeſſors have better learned the <note place="margin">The true cauſe of cruelty for Religion.</note> doctrine of forbearance which hereafter God willing, I will treat of, and have made their <hi>Canons</hi> for uniformitie a little larger, but
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119581:27"/> eſpecially till they better know themſelves, and are affected with their owne ignorances, errors and miſtakings, they are fitter to <hi>Lord</hi> it over their brethren, then bearing their <hi>burthen</hi> to ſerve them in <hi>Love,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 24.</note> and can with more eaſe ſet themſelves to butcher one another, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 2.</note> then to informe, cherriſh and comfort one another, and untill this <hi>ſpirit is abated,</hi> and this inordinate zeale quenched, wee muſt looke <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudg.</hi> 8. 3.</note> for afflictions and perſecutions at the hands of thoſe that are <hi>partakers of the ſame grace with us,</hi> and wait for the comming of the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> from heaven as well as we.</p>
               <p>But what ſhall we ſay? even this the Lord doth, that hee may try <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> us every way, that not onely Infidels and <hi>prophane wretches</hi> may revile, accuſe and wrong us, but even our <hi>familiars and knowne friends,</hi> which have familiarly and ſweetly borne us company in Gods <hi>worſhip;</hi> and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. 13, 14.</note> even they which ſhould be comforters are tormentors. They which are begotten by one <hi>word,</hi> &amp; quickned by one <hi>ſpirit,</hi> cruſh one another to hell, and this is no ſmall triall; for that there ſhould be continuall enmity and ſpirituall warre betwixt the ſeed <hi>of the woman, and the ſeed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Serpent</hi> is no wonder, ſeeing they are as contrary <hi>as light and darkneſse,</hi> but that even the ſeed of the woman ſhould be at ſuch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 14. 15.</note> amongſt themſelves is ſtrange and wonderfull, and ſheweth the greatneſſe of <hi>Satans</hi> malice, the ſtrength of mans corruption, and <note place="margin">All worketh for the beſt.</note> the marvellous operation of Gods grace, which prevaileth even in ſpight of all miſorders, and bringeth great light out of the blackeſt darkneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The ſcandalls in the ſeparated Churches, is no argument to condemne their practice.</head>
               <p>I See no ſuch excellency, or perfection in the ſeparated Churches <note place="margin">SECT. 20.</note> more then in others, but they often runne into many ſcandalous evills and are full of jarres, <hi>emulations</hi> and <hi>contentions;</hi> ſo that <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>9</label> for ought I ſee, a man were as good keepe where he is, as goe to them, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 20.</note> except they were otherwiſe then they are?</p>
               <p>I anſwer firſt, As <hi>Lot</hi> fell into a more grievous ſinne, when onely <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> he and his daughters were in the <hi>cave,</hi> then he ever did when he was <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. 33. 34.</note> in the midſt of the <hi>Sodomites:</hi> And as <hi>David</hi> in his great advancement committed a more foule fact then ever hee did in his former abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ſo there is no eſtate in this world free from temptation and <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. 4.</note> danger neither is our enemy idle, or ſlothfull, to take his opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, from our eſtates, occaſions and condition, but followeth us, to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 1. 7.</note> the gates of heaven, that he may either get us, or cauſe us to <hi>ſcandalize,</hi> by which meanes he may get ſome others.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:119581:28"/>
               <p> When therefore wee ſpeake of ſuch glorious things in the <hi>Church,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> we doe not yet meane that they are a company of <hi>Angels,</hi> or of men free from corruption and <hi>Temptation;</hi> for were it ſo, it needed no ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, <note place="margin">The viſible Church hath no Angelicall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> perfection.</note> nor meanes to helpe, recover and uphold it, but as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, even therefore is a Church-fellowſhip appointed of God to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent frailties and offences, and to purge out ſuch as grow wilfully ſcandalous in evill; and ſuch as will except againſt all ſuch Churches as in whom they find failing in manners, muſt goe ſeeke the Church in <hi>heaven;</hi> for whileſt we are here, we are fraile men, and ſome frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties will ſtill appeare in us, though by the grace of God, many are kept all their life from <hi>ſcandalous</hi> evills.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Papiſts</hi> with like colour object againſt the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> are evill livers, and given to wanton luſts, being full of ſwearing, <note place="margin">The frailties of men no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt a Religion.</note> whoring, drunkenneſſe, theft, &amp;c. But he that is acquainted with both<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> can tell, that even the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in the greater part of them are more frequent in ſuch vices than the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and by their leave, they that will condemne another for an euill, muſt be cleare of it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, elſe their owne mouth will accuſe them.</p>
               <p>But both will object againſt the ſeparated Churches, and ſay you <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>10</label> are but a handfull, and thoſe alſo of culled men, and wee are many, and of all ſorts, as Cities and Countries yeeld, therefore there is no reaſon to expect like holineſſe from us as from you, but if you looke upon the better ſort of us, you ſhall not ſee no ſuch evills breake out in us, as are printed and recorded againſt you?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, firſt, when Chriſt had culled out his wedding gueſts, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> yet there was one which had not a <hi>wedding garment;</hi> ſo though thoſe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 11.</note> men be culled out, yet ſome hypocrites will lurke amongſt them, though they be never ſo poore and contemptible; as <hi>Iudas</hi> did adhere <note place="margin">The ſeparated Churches are not free from hypocrites.</note> unto Chriſt: for though they profeſſe a ſeparation from the open wicked, yet they profeſſe no ſeparation from Hypocrites, neither may, nor can, till they are diſcovered.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Hypocrites, that <hi>turne the Grace of God into wantonneſſe,</hi> are <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iude</hi> 4. 19.</note> moſt forward of all to <hi>ſeparate themſelves from others;</hi> and therefore how <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> can thoſe Churches be free from them?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it is a puniſhment of their former hypocriſie to be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered where they looked for greateſt eſteeme, and ſo being diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of the praiſe of men which they deſired they are in a better way to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 19. 20.</note> come to <hi>Repentance,</hi> then in living amongſt a company as ill as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, where their <hi>viſard</hi> ſhould not have beene plucked off.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, true it is, there may be leſſe evills amongſt the ſeparated, then amongſt the pariſh multitudes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſo I am ſure there is; for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <note place="margin">The ſeparated Churches not ſo evill as the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes.</note> whereas three <hi>Scribes</hi> in a few ſheets of paper did note and diſcourſe of all the evils and <hi>ſcandalls</hi> that fell among the ſeparated in many yeeres. If in the Pariſhes all the evills ſhould be noted and chronicled;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119581:28"/> there had neede at every fifth houſe to dwell a <hi>Scribe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, And though I love not to make compariſons, to cauſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> diſparagement; yet I freely confeſſe and with great comfort ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that there are many in the pariſhes in <hi>England</hi> which <note place="margin">Many Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes excellent in perſonall grace but not in Church order.</note> are of a very godly life and converſation; and ſome that goe as farre therein, as any I ever ſaw in my life. And if I ſhould preferre any of the ſeparated before them in converſation, I ſhould ſpeake againſt my owne conſcience, but in the Church ſtate and order I muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the other before them.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, And yet if a man had a minde to breed and foſter <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> he might cull out a number of <hi>ſcandalls,</hi> which noted men, both <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> and <hi>Profeſſors</hi> in the Pariſhes have fallen into, in a few yeeres, but why ſhould wee make worke for wanton eares? let us rather feare our ſelves, and let him that thinketh <hi>hee ſtandeth, take heed leſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>hee fall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, It is a fault of the profeſſors, that the Churches of ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration are no better; they have lingered, and refuſed to bring their <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> ſoules and bodies into an holy <hi>Temple,</hi> whileſt <hi>Sanballat</hi> and <hi>Tobiah</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezra.</hi> 4. 1. 2.</note> have beene building there, whoſe ſeparation hath rather beene from grace than from corruption; and theſe creeping in under a <hi>ſhew of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iude</hi> 1. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> have filled all with ſcandall, contention and diviſion; whereas if thoſe that had beene ſound and ſincere men, and groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and experienced in the knowledge of God and themſelves, would have beene gathered together, and filled the Sanctuary, there would have beene no roome nor uſe for ſuch inſtruments:</p>
               <p>Wherefore, hereafter doe not you ſit ſtill and controll others, and <note place="margin">It is the fault of the profeſſors, that the ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Churches are no better.</note> doe juſt nothing your ſelves; for I tell you, it is a worke well befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and beſeeming the moſt holieſt and godlieſt people that are in the world, and altogether unfitting and unlawfull for ſuch whoſe lives and converſations are not otherwiſe anſwerable.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, Admit that all the ſeparated Churches have hitherto but <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> dallied and trifled, and puzled themſelves, by reaſon of their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, weakneſſe, and evill carriages, and are rather ſcattering then combining, yet this is no juſt exception againſt the courſe. <hi>Iſrael</hi> ranged about divers yeeres in the <hi>wilderneſſe</hi> and effected nothing, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 1. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> except it were to dig each others <hi>grave,</hi> yet was their generall ayme <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudge</hi> 20. 18. 21. 25. 35.</note> good.</p>
               <p>The eleven <hi>tribes</hi> made two ſallies out againſt the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> and loſt the field, yet was their cauſe good, and in the end they prevailed; <note place="margin">The failings of the ſeparated Churches, ſerve to teach them that now are to begin to doe better.</note> errors in actions are beſt found out, when they are really diſcovered: and if you have ſeene theſe mens failings you owe the more diligence. if you find your owne Church eſtate not right; doth that helpe you to talke of the <hi>Browniſts</hi> contentions? Are you borne to find fault with others, and doe nothing your ſelves? rather you ſhould
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119581:29"/> mend it where they have failed, and when you are come into the right order of a Church, then let other mens harmes teach you.</p>
               <p>And where you have ſeene the ſeparated Churches to be <hi>contentious,</hi> be you more <hi>quiet;</hi> where they have beene full of <hi>diviſions,</hi> cleave you cloſe together; If they would beare nothing, yet beare you one <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers burthen;</hi> If they have beene too cenſorious, be you more chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; If they have lived looſely, live you ſtrictly; If they have beene <note place="margin">An excellent imitation.</note> cold, be you zealous; If they have beene fearefull, be you more ſtout; If they have revolted, ſtand you faſt; And if you thinke all they have done is in hypocriſie, take heed all that you doe be in ſincerity. And thus much for the firſt Generall part of this Treatiſe, tending to direct and perſwade all Chriſtians to come into the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Saints in the order of the Goſpell.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:119581:29"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART OF THE TREATISE; WHEREIN THE TWO MAINE FAILINGS OF the <hi>Rigid Seperation</hi> are reproved, and their Objections anſwered.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The rigid Separationo verrun their courſe in their firſt onſet.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow, that I may not be unjuſt nor partiall, I muſt <note place="margin">SECT. 21.</note> turne my ſelfe to the other ſide, to the ſtrict ſeperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who are even as much beyond the marke, by their over-ſtrained grounds and ſtrait affections, as the Profeſſors in <hi>England,</hi> are ſhort, by their timerous formalitie; ſo as if the one would come a little for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <note place="margin">There would be an excellent harmony, if the ſeparation and the profeſſor could reunite.</note> and the other ſtep backe, and meet both a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the marke, what a ſweet harmony might there be; but who ſhall live to ſee this done? yet to them both, as my loving friends and brethren, I muſt ſpeake, and let God doe what he pleaſeth.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing they are faulty in is, that they not onely condemne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and flie from ſuch evill perſons and things as are found in the Pariſh aſſemblies but alſo condemne, even the moſt godly there, and all religious practices and ordinances they eſteeme none other than an <hi>Idoll</hi> worſhip, and all that uſe it Idolaters, notwithſtanding any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe <note place="margin">The ſeparation have gone too farre.</note> or ſincerity which the perſons have; but how unjuſt their
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119581:30"/> accuſations of the godly people in the aſſemblies are, is evidently ſhewed in a Treatiſe publiſhed by Maſter <hi>I Robinſon,</hi> ſo that of that I need ſay little.</p>
               <p>Indeed Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> and ſome others being under <hi>oppreſsion,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith maketh a <hi>wiſe man madde;</hi> did harſhly and haſtily tumble up all things together eſteeming the fruits and effects <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 9. <hi>H. Barowes</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, <hi>pag.</hi> 112. A dangerous ſentence.</note> of their preaching, with all the comfortable feelings and inward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeings in the ſpirit obtained in the pariſh aſſemblies, to be nothing elſe but a deluſion of <hi>Satan,</hi> to betray their ſoules.</p>
               <p>But words ſpoken or written in haſtie paſſion of the minde and inordinate zeale, muſt not ſtand for Oracles; for, even the holy <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> of God themſelves have recalled ſuch ſpeeches, and choſen rather to confeſſe their owne frailties in uſing them, then adventuring them upon the Church in ſucceeding ages, for a further and remedileſſe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 20. 10. 12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116. 11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 22.</note> danger; as we may ſee in <hi>Moſes, David, Aſaph</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>Though then we eſteeme Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> and the reſt (who firſt ſet upon a ſecond <hi>Lutheran</hi> courſe) otherwiſe good men, and are doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe at reſt with the Lord, yet this muſt be accounted their error. And no man muſt thinke it any diſhonour to them, though they were as good as <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe, if we ceaſe to follow them, where they <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 1.</note> followed <hi>not Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that leaving the Juſtification of the forward and better ſort of people in <hi>England,</hi> to the things written of them in <hi>M. R.</hi> booke, I come to take a viewe of the ordinances which are in the pariſh aſſemblies, to ſee if there be none among them that is Gods, and is uſed without mixture of humane traditions; and though it were a round and ready courſe, to make waſh way of all; yet even <hi>Iehu</hi> had <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 20. 23.</note> ſo much care when he deſtroyed the <hi>Prophets</hi> of <hi>Baal,</hi> as to enquire if none of the Lords Prophets were there.</p>
               <p>So then, though wee be carefull when wee come to the worſhip of God (as we ought to be) that we neither ſubmit our ſelves nor our bodies to human traditions; ſo neither muſt we condemne all for humane <hi>traditions,</hi> which is not comprehended and kept within the limits of a right Church ſtate; for as ſome of the Lords <hi>Prophets</hi> were <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>King.</hi> 18. 13.</note> in <hi>Samaria,</hi> even in the heighth of <hi>Ahabs wickedneſſe,</hi> and ſome holy <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. 18.</note> veſſels in <hi>Babylon,</hi> in the depth of <hi>captivity,</hi> ſo whatſoever may be ſaid of the Church eſtate in <hi>England,</hi> yet there are ſome of Gods Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezra</hi> 1. 7.</note> there, which even in the middeſt of iniquities hath wrought effectually for the ſalvation of many.</p>
               <p>And although all things amongſt them have beene ſo mixed and wrapped in amongſt mens inventions, as that the good and bad can <note place="margin">Preaching in <hi>England</hi> Gods Ordinance.</note> hardly be ſevered; yet there is one thing; which in my judgement, ſtandeth for the moſt part cleare from any evill or abuſe, and that is the preaching of the Word in the aſſemblies of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:119581:30"/>
               <p> Yet not all preaching there, by every <hi>Rhetoricall Ridler,</hi> or pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ling <note place="margin">What Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> may be heard.</note> 
                  <hi>Paraſite,</hi> of which there are too many, but ſuch honeſt and ſincere handling the Word of God, as by ſome few there is uſed, whoſe aime properly and mainly is to beat downe ſins and corruptions, and to build up <hi>and ſtabliſh</hi> in true grace <hi>and godlineſſe;</hi> and who can deny this to be the worke of the Lord, and his ordinance to ſave his <hi>elect?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The efficacy of ſound and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous preaching.</note> though even the beſt of theſe Preachers be in ſome other things awry and miſ-led through the corruption of the times, againſt all which evils and errors of theirs, I am as ready as any to proteſt and beare witneſſe, but they muſt give me leave to ſpare their graces, when I condemne their corruptions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The generall Objection againſt hearing in the Pariſh aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies anſwered.</head>
               <p>THe generall objection is, that all Gods Ordinances are given <note place="margin">SECT. 22.</note> to his Church, and ſo if their Church ſtate be not good, what have they to doe with any of Gods Ordinances, it is out of <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>11</label> 
                  <hi>Sion,</hi> that the Law muſt goe, and ſuch as are of the world have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mich.</hi> 4. 2.</note> to doe to meddle with it.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, firſt, Preaching is not an action that is proper to a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>1</label> Church, neither are all Gods Ordinances ſo given to the Church, as that many of them may not elſewhere be uſed. The <note place="margin">All Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances are not peculiar to the viſible Church.</note> Church muſt be no ingroſſer, nor the world no obtruder; a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous impious wife is more hatefull then a free hearted ſervant.</p>
               <p>And though the Law went firſt out of <hi>Sion;</hi> a proper place, yet now mount <hi>Sion</hi> is every where, and every Chriſtian is both the Temple of the Lord in a ſenſe, as alſo a little mountaine of holineſſe, from <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. 21, 23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.</note> whom the Law of God and his Will muſt flow out upon all juſt occaſions, to neighbours, brethren, countrey-men, ſtrangers, &amp;c. yea, to any, good or bad, that will give attention, and ſo farre are godly Preachers in <hi>England</hi> from blame, becauſe they preach, as that I rather blame them that give over, and deſire from my heart, that where <note place="margin">The increaſe of godly Preachers in <hi>England</hi> is a thing much to be deſired.</note> there is one of theſe plaine and powerfull Preachers, that there were a hundred, and that not onely their Temples, but even their houſes, and all places where people might heare, were filled with the voyce and Word of God, and though this might ſuffice, being rightly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, to anſwer this objection, and to ſhew that preaching may not be ingroſſed by the Church, much leſſe by the officers of the Church, yet becauſe a word is not ſufficient to thoſe that make theſe objections, I willa little more diſtinctly open and proſecute the difference.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:119581:31"/>
               <head>What Preaching is, and who may preach; as alſo where, and to whom.</head>
               <p>PReaching is a reverend declaring of the Will and Word of <note place="margin">SECT. 25.</note> God in many words or in few; or an effectuall evincing and <note place="margin">Preaching what it is. <hi>Iob.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 22. 36. <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 42.</note> ſpeaking to the heart and conſcience, without fearefull with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the portion from any, or immoderate laſhing out that which belongeth to none.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſay it is reverend declaring, &amp;c.</hi> For, every Scripture phraſe and good <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> words, uſed by idle and vaine diſcourſers, is not preaching, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prophaning; that ſpeaking then which is called preaching, muſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 6. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. 18. 19</note> be done with premeditation, and due conſideration of the Author <hi>(God)</hi> of the matter <hi>(his Word)</hi> the end <hi>(his Glory)</hi> and the ſalvation of the hearers. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the Will of God;</hi> wee muſt not preach our owne wills, or empty our ſtomaches againſt ſuch as perſonally oppoſe us, leſt it be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> juſtly aſcribed to humour and paſſion, rather then to the grace of preaching, but when with reverence, onely the Will and Word of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 27. <hi>Iob</hi> 42 7. 8.</note> God is told, that is properly preaching.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In many words, or in few,</hi> I doe not ſay that a ſpeech of an houre long <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> only is preaching; but alſo <hi>a few words, ten words, five words, a word in his place,</hi> being ſeaſonably ſpoken, may be an effectuall <hi>Sermon,</hi> a pithy <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 19. <hi>Prov.</hi> 25. 11. <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 60. 61.</note> exhortation; and whether the ſpeech be long or ſhort, if the Will of God be reverendly declared, and rightly applyed, it is preaching.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is demanded, <hi>who may preach?</hi> And for that I affirme, that every Chriſtian, which hath received any <hi>Talent or gift of God,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> enabling and fitting him thereunto, may at fit occaſions and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, <note place="margin">Who is a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 13. 11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 10. 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 6, 7. <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 1. 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>miniſter the gift he hath received, as a good diſpoſer of Gods ſecrets,</hi> without hiding his talent, or withdrawing himſelfe from <hi>the Lords barveſt, but when a doore is opened,</hi> and an occaſion given, let him that hath <hi>a word of exhortation, ſay on;</hi> And this muſt be done with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian diſcretion according as the <hi>talent</hi> is, ſome men, as they travell and labour in their affaires, to fill with <hi>gracious ſpeeches</hi> and counſell, ſuch as they are ſorted withall: others more eminent and fluent in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 18. 26.</note> ſpeech to doe it more publiquely, as they can, amongſt the multitude, where they dwell or travell, at ſuch time and occaſions, as people meet together, and are willing to heare them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It is demanded, where preaching muſt be? And for that I affirme, that as there is now no <hi>holy or unholy place,</hi> ſo there <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> can be no place ſimply appropriated to it, but it is as lawfull <note place="margin">In what place preaching may be uſed.</note> in one place as in another; and may as lawfully be done <hi>in</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119581:31"/> 
                  <hi>Faires, Market-places, Paſſage boats, Fields, and dwelling houſes;</hi> as in any <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 17. <hi>Mark</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 1.</note> Churches or Temples, provided the place be convenient, and the audience ſilent and attentive.</p>
               <p>The fourth queſtion is, <hi>To whom preaching muſt be uſed,</hi> and for that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> I anſwer, That it may be to any of the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> whether <hi>Iewes,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Who they are, that may be preached unto.</note> 
                  <hi>Turkes, Indians, Nigers, Papiſts</hi> or <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> religious or prophane, one or other, provided, the Preachers matter be ſuited to his audience, and that he be ſuch a <hi>workeman</hi> in <hi>handling</hi> the Word of God, as that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 11. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 15.</note> he give each <hi>his portion thereof, whether terror and judgement,</hi> or <hi>compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and comfort,</hi> taking heed ſtill of that ſentence uſed by the Holy Ghoſt againſt ſuch, as either <hi>juſtifie the wicked, or condemne the righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, the ſumme of all this is thus much, That every Chriſtian <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 17. 15.</note> that hath received a gift of God, for that purpoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> may preach the Word, and ſo conſequently be heard, in any aſſembly, where there may be audience, and upon theſe grounds, which I take to be ſound, I intend to frame theſe enſuing conſequences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the libertie that the Word of God ought to have.</head>
               <p>ANd though now both the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and ſome ignorant <hi>Proteſtants</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">SECT. 24.</note> would have no Word of God ſounded forth by any, but their <note place="margin">No Church nor officers may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſe the word of God.</note> ſelected Clergie; and alſo the <hi>Browniſts</hi> would ingroſſe it into their ſecret aſſemblies, yet the ſame key which unlocked the old <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques</hi> Latine box, wherein they kept all the <hi>Lat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie</hi> from the Letter of the Scriptures, muſt now be uſed to free the preaching thereof out of the priſon, wherein theſe ingroſſers have bound in chaines the very <hi>Goſpel of our Lord Ieſus,</hi> that if there ſhould riſe up a man as learned <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 18.</note> and eminent as <hi>Paul;</hi> yet, except he would come into their order, he muſt remaine ſilent all his life long.</p>
               <p>But the Word of God muſt not thus be bound, nor the graces of his ſervanrs muſt not be buried in ſilence alwayes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the light muſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 33. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 18.</note> be ſet on <hi>the Table,</hi> and the <hi>glory of the Lord</hi> muſt be ſhewed, though vaine man be forced to couch under board, neither is it much mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3 30. 31.</note> though the <hi>greateſt that is borne of woman,</hi> doe <hi>decreaſe,</hi> as long as the <hi>Saviour</hi> of the world <hi>increaſeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, then here falleth to the ground that opinion of theirs which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> tie the preaching of the Word to an order of Miniſtery; for as it is certaine that there hath beene no univerſall office of Miniſtery ſince the Apoſtles, but all Miniſters ſince have had their office bounded <note place="margin">No univerſall Miniſtry now.</note> within the limits of their particular flockes, and the ſucceſſion from the Apoſtles, is none otherwiſe now, then in doctrine, faith
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119581:32"/> and grace, ſo as now it is not poſſible that a Church ſhould ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a lawfull ordinary Miniſtery; which is raiſed or made by any other then themſelves; and therefore, if preaching may not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note place="margin">Preaching muſt not be tyed to Miniſters.</note> an ordinary office of Miniſtery, how ſhall there ever be faith or grace, or matter prepared for a Church, except ſuch Chriſtians as have the knowledge and feare of God, may publiſh and ſpread the ſame amongſt their neighbours for their edification and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion?</p>
               <p>Secondly, from theſe grounds we ſee how abſurd the opinion of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the <hi>ſeparation</hi> is, that tie all preaching and publiſhing the Goſpell to ſuch as are of their handfull, which are few in number, and leſſe in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; and this of all other would make the miſerableſt ſcarcity: for whereas in ſome whole <hi>Shires</hi> of this Land, there is ſcarce one of them, <note place="margin">Preaching not tyed to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> and in other places two or three in ſome townes, and thoſe for the moſt part, ſuch as ſcarce know well their principles? What a miſery ſhould all the people about them be in, if no Word of God, nor ſound of the Goſpel muſt be heard, til they were able and willing, and could intend to preach it; but let not the Word of God be thus bound.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by this ground alſo, that every Chriſtian that hath a gift <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> may uſe it for the edification of others: it followeth, that if the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and Kingdome where we live take no publique courſe for prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, yet the <hi>Goſpel</hi> may ſtill ſound in families, and from neighbour to neighbour; and alſo if there be any that cannot or will not come <note place="margin">Though pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like preaching become vaine or fraile, yet private muſt not. <hi>Heſt.</hi> 4. 14. <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 42.</note> to publique preaching, or that the publique preaching begin ſo to be fraughted and ſtuffed with policie, eloquence, and vaine oſtentation, as that it becomes unprofitable, &amp;c. Yet ſtill the word of God is not bound, but <hi>helpe commeth another way,</hi> and when they hold their peace that ſhould ſpeake, the mouth of the <hi>very ſtones are opened.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, it followeth from theſe grounds, that Kings and Princes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> may not onely themſelves ſtudy and preach the Word, as did King <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>Fox in Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. pag.</hi> 100. 110. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Salomon,</hi> and <hi>Oſwaldus,</hi> King of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> but alſo it teacheth them to approve, protect and maintaine by their civill power, the preaching of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and ſpreading the knowledge of Chriſt, by all meanes, and by all them to whom God hath given a gift thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <note place="margin">It is a worke becomming a King to preach the Word.</note> whether they be Lawyers, Phyſicians or other <hi>mechanicall</hi> men that are able and doe it orderly, and to be ſo farre from tying it to a place or houre, as that they ſhould rejoyce to have it ſound in private houſes, <hi>Ferry boats, Faires</hi> and <hi>Markets,</hi> being done without civill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order <note place="margin">And good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment muſt promote prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wayes.</note> order and detraction from men of greater eminencie, remembring the example of that godly Magiſtrate, <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was ſo farre from forbidding <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> to <hi>propheſie,</hi> (though <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> a good man requeſted him) as that he alſo wiſhed that <hi>all the Lords people could alſo</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 11. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>propheſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And laſtly, according to our proper intent, <hi>If every gifted Chriſtian</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119581:32"/> 
                  <hi>may preach where they can have audience;</hi> then if any of the Preachers in <hi>England</hi> be Chriſtians, and have a gift to preach (both or any of <note place="margin">No gift may be loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> which to deny, were ſhamefull) they may then preach the Word in any place where the people are aſſembled of what kinde ſoever, or for what cauſe ſoever, and conſequently in their pariſh Churches where the people of the pariſh meet, to uſe <hi>Divine ſervice,</hi> and other <hi>Rites</hi> eſtabliſhed by Law, I ſay, when all is done, if yet they will give their attendance, to heare a <hi>meſſage from God,</hi> and that there be one of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3. 20. <hi>Iob.</hi> 33. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>a thouſand</hi> there ſo fitted, he may and ought there to declare his <hi>Word of exhortation,</hi> and it is lawfull and good for any godly man to come and heare him. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 15.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The particular objections againſt hearing in the pariſh aſſemblies anſwered.</head>
               <p>NOw though theſe grounds and conſequences doe clearely <note place="margin">SECT. 25.</note> evince the truth of this point, and alſo we know that ſo long as the ground and foundation of a thing ſtandeth, there is little good to be done againſt the thing by other working, yet becauſe this age is fuller of catching wits to cavill againſt ſome appendixes and leaves of the tree; then of ſolid and able men to undermine and wade into the root of things, therefore I will apply my ſelfe to goe a little aſide from the currant of the matter to anſwer their exceptions.</p>
               <p>The Preachers in the aſſemblies receive an unlawfull office from <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>12</label> the <hi>Prelates,</hi> and they which heare them approve of their office, ſince they preach by it.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, firſt, this and a thouſand ſuch exceptions cannot remove <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> the ground before laid downe; for it is his Chriſtian ſtate and gifts that maketh him a Preacher, and not his office; whether it be right or wrong: It is indeed his ſin to take ſuch an office from the <hi>Prelates,</hi> and a further ſin to execute the office, as he doth in the cuſtomes and rites of the Church, but no man can ſay this ſinne maketh him ceaſe <note place="margin">If any of the Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> have gifts, and be Chriſtians, they may preach.</note> to be a Chriſtian, ſo long as in his generall courſe and carriage hee ſhewes himſelfe honeſt and conſcionable, but wee are in charitie to eſteeme it an infirmity in him which the times ſway him to, and no more, and we are to cover it in his other vertues, and love and reſpect him ſtill for the good he hath, and not caſt him off for ſome failings, leſt we be <hi>ſerved ſo our ſelves.</hi> Indeed, if for every ſuch error and failing we will ranke them amongſt thoſe <hi>which hate to be reformed,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 16. 17.</note> we may then conclude apace, that they may not take Gods <hi>covenant in their mouths.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:119581:33"/>
               <p> And yet were they ſuch (as they are not) yet ſo long as their gifts <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> remaine they may be heard, as well as the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſies,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 3. 4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 14. 15.</note> the evill and corrupt teachers in <hi>Corinth;</hi> for though themſelves ſin by uſing the Name and Word of God, whileſt they neither feare nor obey him, ye till God taketh away their gifts and facultie, I ſee not but an uſe may be made of it.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing a man of knowledge, judgement and utterance with <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> gravity, authority and power, is a compleat Preacher, as was <hi>Apollo,</hi> whether he have an office or no office, a good office or an evill office, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 18. 24. 25. An office no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to prove or diſprove a mans prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</note> it is to no more purpoſe to bring in his office, to prove the lawfulneſſe or unlawfulneſſe of his preaching, than to alledge againſt a man the unlawfulneſſe of his marriage, to diſprove his workemanſhip in his Trade, and as abſurd it is for to enquire into the office of him that is to preach before we heare him, as to enquire into an Artificers marriage, before we will either acknowledge him for a worke-man, or imploy him in any buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>And when a man is to make any good and profitable ſpeech, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the in <hi>Law, Phiſique,</hi> or <hi>divinitie,</hi> he is like to prove the wiſer man, that asketh what he ſaith rather then whence he is.</p>
               <p>Neither can any man be ſaid to approve of their office, except he <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> joyne with them in ſuch things as appertaine to their office, as doth their ſervice and ceremonies, but preaching is an accidentall thing, and no part of the office properly, but an ornament or appendix about <note place="margin">Preaching ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall to the Prieſt-hood in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note> it, which may be wanting, and yet the Miniſter a full officer in the order of <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> and though he never preach whileſt he lives, yet the Law cannot tax him for not performing his office; and thus God hath even provided of purpoſe; that his owne ordinance of praying, ſhould not be bundled up in the bedroll of humane rites, but be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed of the builders, as a needleſſe thing, that his owne honour might be the more, when the power thereof is ſeene.</p>
               <p>But both Miniſters and People here profeſſe, that they preach by <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>13</label> vertue of their office?</p>
               <p>They alſo profeſſe, that all that will not joyne with them in their <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> ſervice and Sacraments are Schiſmatiques, but they may be deceived in both, for any thing I know, and if they will thus conclude ſtill, that <note place="margin">Learne wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by other mens abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> their Preachers preach by vertve of their offices, and erre about it, I muſt not erre with them, ſince I know, that all the offices in the world cannot make a man a Preacher, an office indeed, if it be right makes him their Preacher which have choſen him, but hee is ſtill a Preacher, and preacheth onely by vertue of his gift.</p>
               <p>But they take a licenſe from the Biſhops to preach, and therefore <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>14</label> they are their meſſengers, and not Chriſts?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, firſt, if the licenſe they take of the Biſhops be onely or <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> properly to allow them to preach which are fit thereunto, I have
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119581:33"/> nothing to ſay againſt it, but wiſh they alſo would licenſe the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to aſſemble together, and uſe the Ordinances freely and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note place="margin">The Biſhops li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe no let to preaching.</note> danger; and I would be ſorry any man ſhould be any thing the more afraid to uſe that liberty, becauſe they had licenſed it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is not meet that every one ſhould hand over head goe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> preach publiquely, without ſome triall and approbation of ſome grave and learned men.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, If the licenſe enjoyne them any unlawfull thing, they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ought not to doe it, but if it either enjoyne, or permit them to preach, they may out of doubt doe it, notwithſtanding the licenſe, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever elſe is in the licenſe enjoyned.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Admit it be their ſinne to take this licenſe, yet ſince they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> may lawfully in reſpect of God, and the right of the thing preach without it, why not alſo with it? as well as a man may live with his lawfull wife, which he had lawfully married before, though ſome oppreſſing tyrant ſhould force him to take licenſe anew from him to live with her?</p>
               <p>Fithly, And what if no man ſhould be ſuffered to uſe conceived <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> prayers in his family without examination and licenſe of the Biſhops, and that men for their ſafety therein ſhould take licenſe from them for it? I ſuppoſe there is no man will ſay they muſt now ceaſe to pray, or that it is unlawfull, being godly men, for their wives and families to joyne with them; even ſo the Biſhops licenſe, not making it lawfull in reſpect of God for a man of gifts to preach, but onely ſafe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the oppoſitions of men, whether it be obtained or not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, the gifts of God muſt ſtill be uſed.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, The Biſhops, or their ſubſtitutes doe alſo give licenſe to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                  <hi>Phyſitians</hi> and Schoole-maſters, yet I never heard of any that held, that the taking phyſique from one, or learning from the other, was any approbation or ſupportance to the Biſhops unlawfull power.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, As <hi>Peter</hi> was both Satan and an Apoſtle of Chriſt, ſo theſe men in a ſenſe may be ſaid to be the meſſengers and Miniſters, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 23.</note> both of Chriſt and the Biſhops; of Chriſt in preaching his Word ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaſure of grace given them by him, and of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in taking power from them, and performing humane rites and <hi>Traditions</hi> enjoyned by them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:119581:34"/>
               <head>Other objections againſt hearing anſwered.</head>
               <p>BUt many of theſe Preachers are of evill life, and preach nothing <note place="margin">SECT. 25.</note> but verball Sermons, fraught with oftentation and pomp of <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>15</label> words, wherein there is neither power nor plaineneſſe?</p>
               <p>It muſt needs be confeſſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that not one of twentie of them that <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> are trained up in the Univerſity are fit to be Preachers ſeeing it is not humane learning that maketh a man a Preacher; but other helps of nature and grace, without which humane learning makes a man play the foole rather then the wiſe man; and indeed, if a man have <note place="margin">Humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning maketh not a man a Preacher.</note> not naturall parts and graces of modeſtie and humility, whereby to overſhadow and ſwallow up his humane learning, he rather ſeemeth vicious then vertuous in any thing he doth, and it is one of the evills of this age and that which drives many to <hi>Atheiſme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> that all Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity Schollers that will but profeſſe <hi>Divinity</hi> may ſtep into pulpits as Apprentizes into <hi>Trades,</hi> though they have neither grace nor wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, nor any naturall abilities, but having read over, and got by heart ſome <hi>Antiquities,</hi> partly <hi>Divine</hi> partly <hi>Philoſophicall,</hi> and partly <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous;</hi> they can ſometimes powre them out together, and ſo get a name of fine Schollers among the carnall multitude; but all theſe verball diſcourſes of ſuch fine Schollers, being uſed yeere after yeere, <note place="margin">Many preach, but doe no good thereby.</note> and joyned with a carnall and diſſolute life, ſerve for nothing but for oſtentation and name, never converting or drawing any from their ſinnes, but rather lulling them faſt aſleepe in the cradle of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, wherein they are carryed to hell, whileſt neither themſelves nor their <hi>blinde watchmen</hi> are aware of the danger. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But ſuch ſtraglers and ſtriplings I will not perſwade any man to heare, eſpecially ſince there are others who are no runners to this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierem.</hi> 14. 15, 16. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 23. 21.</note> work without their errant, who even in zeale of God, and in deſire of the ſalvation of men, being endued with the guifts of <hi>Knowledge, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Vtterance, Gravitie,</hi> and authority of ſpeech; as alſo of a godly &amp; ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 8. 10. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 7.</note> life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſet themſelves to ſhame all vices &amp; work out the corruptions out of the vaine heart of man, and to drop into them, and draw them into the grace and feare of God, whoſe carefull and effectuall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are not in vaine, but they doe daily wound and weaken the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 18.</note> Kingdome of <hi>Satan</hi> and <hi>Sinne,</hi> and advance the Power and Scepter of Chriſt, at leaſt in the hearts and converſation of many, and leave ſuch an impreſſion in the hearts of the moſt obſtinate, that they <hi>ſavour the ſentence of their condemnation</hi> daily from them, and goe up and down <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 15, 16.</note> as men condemned with their halters about their necks; and ſuch
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119581:34"/> kind of Preachers onely would I perſwade to the hearing of, without reſpect to townes or pariſhes; but let civill order give place to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <note place="margin">Civill orders may not anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilatc Gods Ordinances.</note> neceſſitie, and rather beare a civill <hi>mulct,</hi> then neglect a ſpirituall Ordinance.</p>
               <p>And the exception concerning the ſhallow and inſufficiency of the other, maketh no more againſt them, then the trifling <hi>Prophets, who</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierem.</hi> 23. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>ran</hi> before they were ſent, were a juſt objection againſt the Prophet <hi>Ieremy,</hi> who was ſent of the Lord.</p>
               <p>But the Preachers in the pariſhes preach not the whole truth, but <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>16</label> run into many errors and abſurdities, either to pleaſe the State, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the times, or advance themſelves, and yet a man may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them, and how then ſhall he heare them?</p>
               <p>I anſwer firſt, It is not meet to preach all truths to all men, but <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> firſt their conſciences muſt be urged with that which they ſtand moſt need of, and that they can conceive of, and to buſie their heads about other high matters, before they have learned the <hi>doctrine of faith</hi> and repentance, and have reformed their wayes, were even juſt as if one <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 1, 2.</note> ſhould give a man an oration in <hi>Latine</hi> to conſtrue, which knew never a letter of the <hi>Booke,</hi> and where ſuch teaching is ordinarily uſed, you have a number that can ſpie out faults in others, but very few that are truly reformed themſelves.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Niether can it be expected of any <hi>Paſtor</hi> or <hi>Preacher</hi> in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> this world or fraile life, that he ſhould never let fall any errors or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound poſitions; for, <hi>Who knoweth the errors of this life?</hi> and who can <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 12.</note> wonder; ſeeing the formall ſtate hath here ſo long prevailed (and that with ſuch proſperity and applauſe) if even ſome of Gods holy <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> at ſome time, <hi>ſay even as they?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 2, 3, 13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But if there be any who make it their drift and cuſtome to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound and maintaine evill practices and unſound grounds, and to inveigh againſt the faithfull ſervants of God, ſuch are to be <hi>taken heed of,</hi> but ſuch, whoſe drift and common courſe, is ſoundly to interpret and apply the Word of God, beating downe mans corruption and ſtabliſhing them in grace and holineſſe (though in ſome things they ſwarve from the rules of truth) yet they may and muſt be heard.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Errors <hi>muſt ſometimes</hi> be let fall, even in the pureſt and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> beſt reformed Churches, for the triall of the faithfulls ſoundneſſe, and <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 19</note> the diſcovery of Hypocrites, that the love of the truth in the one may the more gloriouſly be diſplayed and the want of love to the truth in the other may be puniſhed with ſtrong and <hi>conſtant believing of lies</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 10. 11.</note> ſo that it is better for a man to be ſoundly grounded in the truth and ſetled ſincerely to love it, that ſo he may diſcerne and reſiſt errors, rather then once imagine he can live where none is taught.</p>
               <p>Fourthly Neither may we nouriſh in our ſelves a perſwaſion that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> all or any of the godly Preachers in <hi>England</hi> preach and declare thoſe <note place="margin">Conſtrue all things in the beſt part.</note>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:119581:35"/> unſound poſitions and unwritten verities, for fleſhly ends; as favour of men, love of advancement, and the like; but rather charity ſhould teach us to impute it to their ignorance, feare and humane frailtie, which is more or leſſe in us all, remembring, that they which make <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 42. 21.</note> ſuch evill conſtructions of other mens actions, are againe afterwards paid home with like meaſure.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Neither are we bound to reprove alwaies every error and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> abſurdity we heare, but to conſider as well our place, calling, intereſt and authority that we have in the place or with the perſon, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently what likelihood there is of doing good by our reproofe; <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 12.</note> for if wee caſt admonitions abroad at all adventures, without conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering theſe circumſtances, wee rather expoſe our ſelves to ſcorne, and the Word of God to reproach and ſcorne, then doe any good at all.</p>
               <p>But though it might be lawfull to heare the Preachers in <hi>England,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>17</label> yet it is better to forbeare it, becauſe of offence?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, To be offended at a thing in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſenſe, is not <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> when one is diſcontent, angry, or vexed for a thing; but when he <note place="margin">What it is to give offence. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 15. 21.</note> ſtaggereth and ſtumbleth ſo at anothers practice; as that he is drawne by his example, to imitate him, contrary to the judgement and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of his owne heart and conſcience, but ſuch offences (in this particular eſpecially) doe hardly any of the ſtrict ſeparation take, but <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 10. 11.</note> the worſt hurt it can doe them, is but onely to anger them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Offences</hi> are alwayes given, either in things evill, or <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> things indifferent; but to preach and heare the Word of God, is <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 13. Preaching and Hearing the Word are no actions of indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent nature.</note> neither evill nor indifferent and leaſt of all can it be thought indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, but an action wherein the name of God is ſo much uſed as it is in that, muſt either be a proper part of his ſervice, or elſe a horrible blaſphemy; and taking his name in vaine, which farre be it from us to thinke.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Admit it were indifferent (which cannot be) yet in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> giving <hi>offence</hi> in matters indifferent, we have reſpect onely to the <hi>weake,</hi> of which there are thouſands in the aſſemblies in <hi>England,</hi> which by our example in refuſing to heare their Preachers, are often drawne ſo to refuſe both them and their teaching, as that they have <note place="margin">It is onely the weake that take offence.</note> even been left without all help means &amp; to repent and believe the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> for the ſoules of whom the ſtrict ſeparation have much no anſwer.</p>
               <p>But it were a great diſparagement and ſhame in the ſeparation, to plead weakneſſe; and ſure I am, they are ſtrong enough to hold the concluſion in this and many other points, how weake ſoever they may prove in their grounds, or proſecutings and practice of the things they hold.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Experience hath taught, that the moſt part of ſuch as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> have lightly and contemptuouſly refuſed to heare the godly Preachers
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119581:35"/> in <hi>England,</hi> have had little eſteeme of preaching amongſt themſelves, but have had more delight to buſie themſelves in triviall controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies to try their wits then to have their hearts wrought upon by ſound <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 5. 6.</note> and wholſome doctrine; the event of all hath beene, that they have had no peace in themſelves, nor brought no profit to others.</p>
               <p>But we ſee what commeth by giving way to heare Sermons in the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>18</label> aſſemblies, even this; that one thing ſo followeth another, that with Sermons they partake alſo in <hi>ſervice ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Sacraments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> yea joyn in all their corruptions, and at laſt turne prophane and looſe in their lives and converſation alſo?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, firſt, this may be true, and for it the Churches of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>1</label> are much to be blamed that will force every one that heareth a <hi>Sermon</hi> in the Pariſh aſſemblies, to confeſſe it to be a ſin, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt repentance for it, or elſe exclude him quite from their ſociety and <note place="margin">The Churches of the ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are faulty in the going away of their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</note> felowſhip, and ſo ſome of their members, out of a good affection, having heard ſome <hi>Sermons,</hi> and not beene convinced of evill in it; have undergone their cenſure, and afterward walked alone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late men, catching here and there a crum where they could catch it til at length by perſwaſion of friends and weakneſſe in themſelves, they have beene drawne into ſome practices apparantly evill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereas if they had beene lovingly borne with in their ſuſpected evill: no doubt many of them would either have returned to the ſociety whereof they were, or ſome other like, or elſe ſtill have retained in themſelves a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend reſpect and longing after the pure order and ordinances of the <hi>Goſpell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, what if ſome have made it a path-way to ſerve their <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> luſts? that is no argument againſt it; but onely ſheweth the vanity and unſtability of ſome men: when <hi>Abſalom</hi> made <hi>ſacrificing</hi> a cloke <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 8. 12.</note> for his <hi>rebellion,</hi> was ſacrificing any thing the more to be diſliked in thoſe dayes? Yea, what evill is there almoſt that goeth not with ſome <hi>pretence</hi> of good apparantly? It ſheweth indeed the vanity, lightneſſe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 7. 14.</note> and unſtability of ſome men, who neither had diſtinct rules and grounds to goe by, nor were conſcionable, nor carefull to attend on God for his direction; but as they ran lightly to ſeparation upon ſome humour or diſcontented motion, ſo againe they left it as wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonly, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 14.</note> when a new toy tooke them in the head againe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, And indeed, even this very thing ſhould make the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Churches of the ſeparation looke better about them, and take heed of drawing young heads and unſtable wits with leſſe honeſty to them; for the truth is, they ſo dote upon ſeparation, as that if a man have it, <note place="margin">The <hi>Br.</hi> make an Idoll of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Paration<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> though hee have all other points and parts of <hi>Religion</hi> to learne and ſeeke, yet he may even for it onely be admired and advanced amongſt them; but if he be not wholly ſeparated, but will retaine ſome love and reſpect to ſome perſons and things in the Pariſh aſſemblies, had
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119581:36"/> he all the holineſſe and Religion that elſe poſſibly he could have, yet he muſt never be admitted amongſt them, but held out as an <hi>Idolator,</hi> and one under the power of darkneſſe, and of <hi>Satans</hi> kingdome. And though for this their unreaſonable <hi>dotage</hi> they have beene beaten ſore with their owne <hi>rods,</hi> when they that came to them with cenſorious mouthes, againſt all practices in the Pariſh aſſemblies, have within a <note place="margin">They have been beaten with their owne rod.</note> few yeeres returned, railing worſe at them; and though they have been adviſed, not to meaſure men by one particular practice, but have an eye to the generall worke of Gods grace in them, yet all in vaine, for they will not heare not regard, <hi>charme the Charmer never ſo wiſely.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58. 4, 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, their going to the <hi>holy Supper</hi> in the aſſemblies, ſheweth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſtill their ignorance, that come back from the ſeparation even as wiſe as they went to them, not knowing what religious actions are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to Church communion, and what are common to be uſed every <note place="margin">Communion in the L. ſupper a Church action.</note> where, nor regarding any more with whom at the <hi>Table of the Lord</hi> they feaſt, then amongſt whom they ſtand to heare a good ſpeech; ſince the thing is plaine, that thoſe that keepe that feaſt together, muſt be united to Chriſt, and one to another by the ſpirit; but they that to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 17.</note> manifeſt no more then the patience to heare, there can be no juſt ſcruple, though amongſt a hundred, there are not two that have any ſigne of grace or holineſſe.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, At a word, as <hi>Iacobs</hi> Poſteritie might lawfully enjoy that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  <hi>bleſsing</hi> which their father got of <hi>Iſack,</hi> by lying and deceit, and as a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. 19. 20.</note> poore man may receive and uſe that money which is given him by one that got it by extortion or bribery; ſo, though even all and every <note place="margin">The Preachers in <hi>England</hi> ſin, to get liberty to preach.</note> of the Preachers in <hi>England</hi> doe ſome evill that good may come of it, and ſubmit themſelves to humane traditions, which they ought to ſhun, that they may preach the Word, yet the good they doe, being at any time ſevered from the evill and their preaching from their <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> they may then be heard, and reverently reſpected, and the Lord in his mery pardon their evill, and <hi>heale them,</hi> whoſe hearts are <hi>upright</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30. 18, 19, 20.</note> with him, though many failings have beene in their courſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>They that goe about to juſtifie the Miniſters in</hi> England <hi>in their Office, drive men from the Church altogether.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd now I will ſay no more at this time for the juſtifying <note place="margin">SECT. 27.</note> of hearing in the Pariſh aſſemblies, till I ſee this ground taken a way, and the anſwers to theſe objections over-turned, which if they could be with evidence of truth, let the Lord be a gainer, and let me be a loſer.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119581:36"/>
               <p> I am not ignorant, that the common way which is uſed to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade <note place="margin">The office of the Miniſtry in <hi>England</hi> is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ight.</note> men to heare them, is to defend and juſtifie their Calling and Office of Miniſtery to be of divine inſtitution.</p>
               <p>And to prove it, ſome deſcend to their parents which ſet them to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſchoole, others to their aptneſſe and willingneſſe to learne, and to their choice in the Univerſities for their reading and ſtudies, and deſire to preach &amp;c. in all which I know the providence of God worketh but all this ſerveth but for the ability and fitneſſe, and is not eſſentiall to the externall office at all, which is an outward ſtate or ſtation confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon him for ſome inward and eminent gift or quality.</p>
               <p>Others there are, who will fetch a ſucceſſive Miniſtery from <hi>Adam</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> lineally to reach to this day, others come lower and fetch <note place="margin">They that plead for ſucceſſion cannot ſatisfie the conſcience.</note> the pedigree from <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and will have thoſe holy fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to leap over all the <hi>Popes</hi> heads and be borne up with both their ſhoulders for a thouſand yeeres and upward, till in the daies of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> a piece thereof fell to the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>biſhop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> from which wind-fall bough all thoſe thouſands of ſpirituall functions now in <hi>England</hi> have ſprouted and ſpread themſelves, untill it is become a <hi>Proteſtant Miniſtery,</hi> and defies thoſe many fathers from whom their <hi>branches</hi> tooke life, and will now be of themſelves, and conteſt with <note place="margin">See <hi>D. Maſons</hi> Booke of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſec.</note> the <hi>Pope,</hi> from whoſe chaire their authority is derived.</p>
               <p>Others more aſhamed of that old dung-hill of <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> will goe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> but to <hi>Luther</hi> for their pedigree, whom they fancy to be ſome new <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> and ſo might create a new Miniſtery; but as neither the ſoundneſſe of <hi>Luthers</hi> doctrine, nor the temperature of his affections, <note place="margin">Succeſſion from <hi>Luther</hi> a ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> was <hi>Apoſtolike;</hi> ſo he neither did nor might create any univerſall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, whoſe Dioces could reach into this <hi>Iland,</hi> and if he ſhould, yet ſtill it muſt be of the nature, (though not of the name,) with that of the <hi>Romiſh race,</hi> and not one jot neerer to Chriſts inſtitution.</p>
               <p>Others will have their very office and function to ſtand in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and approbation of the pariſh. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>But, firſt, as the pariſhes are unfit and uncapable of making a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, <note place="margin">The approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the pariſh no part or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters office.</note> ſo they doe nothing at all therein, but are as meere patients, to ſuffer whom the <hi>Dioceſan</hi> pleaſeth to put in or pull out.</p>
               <p>Secondly, and indeed, who knoweth not that all the pariſh Vicars and Parſons in the Land, doe ſolemnly receive and take their charge, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> orders, office and function from the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and their adherents, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may come to adminiſter in any pariſh whatſoever.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they ſtand at the will of the <hi>Biſhop;</hi> ſo as if he bid them be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſilent, they dare ſay no more. Now, if the conſent and approbation of the pariſh be ſuch a divine inſtitution as they pretend, how perfidious <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 15. <hi>Ast.</hi> 5. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 28. 29 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 16.</note> and unconſtant are they with God that at the word of a <hi>mortall</hi> man dare neglect that calling of the <hi>Lord?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At a word, when men ſhall ſcruple at hearing their Sermons, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:119581:37"/> they can ſatisfie them no other way, but by alledging their office and function, which neither is agreeable to Scripture, nor to it ſelfe, but hanged together by vaine ſuppoſitions, and popiſh aſſertions, which ſerve ten times more to ſtaine and blame it, then to juſtifie it; what can they looke for in the event but to ſee themſelves deſpiſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned <note place="margin">It is beſt to cover the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of the Miniſters of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</note> for pleading ſo lame a caſe, and whither ſhall men be driven hereby but to ſeparation and Anabaptiſme, or elſe to worſe matters?</p>
               <p>But when this law and lawleſſe office is paſſed by, and covered in a ſerious <hi>love</hi> of their graces, (as the Lord, no doubt, covereth it in Chriſt Jeſus) every man will lay his hand on his mouth; for <hi>in their gifts and graces</hi> of preaching, no man can deny the Lord to be in them indeed, and in ſuch actions as God eminently ſhewes his grace, we <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 24. 25.</note> may be evidently preſent in perſon and affection.</p>
               <p>Neither can there be any other ſucceſſion from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Primitive Churches,</hi> otherwiſe then in faith, gifts and graces, ſince their <note place="margin">6. Succeſſion is onely in faith and grace. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 8, 9. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 11. 12, 13.</note> office is wholly ceaſed, and he is now the lineall ſucceſſor of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> which commeth neereſt to them in gifts, graces and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; And what in this world can be more abſurd, than to make every popiſh Prieſt and idle Dunce, (which hath got onely an up ſtart <hi>ordination</hi> of ſome antiquitie) to be the true ſucceſſor of the holy <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> when they have neither grace in their hearts, wit in their heads, or honeſty in their converſation: and if the office be that <note place="margin">No grace, no ſucceſſion.</note> which muſt be pleaded to juſtifie all their miniſtrations; even all theſe blind Prieſts and verball Teachers have as good reaſon for their ſtanding as the beſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The ſtrict ſeparation cannot hold together amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</head>
               <p>ANd as theſe men have been too extreme and cenſorious in their <note place="margin">SECT. 28.</note> ſeparation, ſo are they in their Church covenant and combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by meanes whereof they need no other perſecutors then <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> themſelves; for their owne ſwords enter ſo faſt into their own bowels, as that if all the perſecutions in this world were againſt them, it could hardly make ſuch havocke as they make amongſt themſelves, I meane not in regard of civill puniſhments, for that power they have not any <note place="margin">The ſeparation eat up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note> where, and if they had, and ſhould have ſuch ſpirits in their civill judgements, as they have in their ſpirituall cenſures, the one halfe of them had need to become hangmen, but it is onely in regard of their extreme worrying one another, for every difficult queſtion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſall practice, in ſolemne and vehement charges, quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and captious invectives, ſhort and ſudden <hi>excommunications,</hi> in all
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119581:37"/> which they have ſo wearied and waſted themſelves, that a man may truely ſay of them, that no ſociety under any perſecution (warre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) did ever decreaſe and ruinate as they doe.</p>
               <p>And as the profeſſors in <hi>England</hi> are juſtly taxed for living in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> without a ſociety of faithfull Chriſtians in a Church eſtate, and without the order and diſcipline, &amp;c. ſo theſe men may be as well blamed for bringing themſelves to confuſion, by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their wits, and abuſing both their <hi>gifts</hi> and the <hi>diſcipline</hi> of Chriſt to their owne ſhame and ruine, and to the diſhonour of Chriſt, the peaceable Law-giver of his Church.</p>
               <p>And although for the ancient of them, who now live (as alſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the firſt <hi>Engliſh Anabaptiſts,</hi> who harpe all upon one ſtring) if I had <hi>the tongues of men and Angels,</hi> yet have I no hope to change their <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 1. 2.</note> mindes, or moderate their affections, ſince no counſell, warning, or experience can teach them any thing, but ſtill bitterneſſe is in their hearts, and violence is in their tongues; and they will rather quarrell with ten men for one triffe, then lovingly agree with any man in any thing.</p>
               <p>Yet, to prevent ſuch as ſhall come after, from running their courſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and that their extremities may die with their perſons (as they have already begun) and the truth they hold receive no wrong, I will diſcover, and put to ſilence that opinion and practice of theirs, which breakes, divides and rents them aſunder daily, notwithſtanding all other truthes and appearance of zeale which is amongſt them.</p>
               <p>It is held and practiſed amongſt them for a maxime, <hi>That they</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">A dangerous opinion.</note> 
                  <hi>muſt ſuffer no evill, in any man, nor no appearance of evill;</hi> but every one that is of them muſt jump with them in judgement and practice, and he muſt not goe a foote before them, nor come one inch behind <note place="margin">This rule they ordinarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes.</note> them, but muſt in all things ſay as they ſay, and doe as they doe, and if he ſwarve from them in any thing which they thinke to be truth, they will ſolemnly admoniſh him, and if hee will not repent, they will forthwith excommunicate him, be the evill never ſo ſmall and doubtfull, and whatſoever other graces or holineſſe be in the perſon, or whatſoever bands betwixt him and them either in grace or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the unreaſonableneſſe whereof I will reprove by theſe reaſons following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:119581:38"/>
               <head>There are ſome ſinnes that muſt be borne in the Church.</head>
               <p>EXcept ſome ſins may be borne in the Church, why ſpeaketh the <note place="margin">SECT. 29.</note> holy Ghoſt thus to the Churches? <hi>Beare yee one anothers burthen,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Love covereth a multitude of ſinnes, forſake not the fellowſhip, but exhort one another daily;</hi> Why rather ſuffer yee not wrong? If he had meant to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 7.</note> make ſuch ſhort work as theſe men do, he would have ſaid bear with no man, love no man that is faulty, ſuffer no wrong, but abandon every fellowſhip and perſon that hath any evill in him not reformed.</p>
               <p>If no evills in the Church may be borne, then why did not <hi>Paul</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> write to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> to caſt out more offenders then the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous man,</hi> ſeeing there were thoſe that wronged their brethren, and <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 1. 2, 3. &amp; 6. 6. 8. &amp; 10. 12. &amp; 11. 22.</note> went <hi>to Law</hi> with them <hi>amongſt the heathen rulers,</hi> others that went to <hi>the Idol feaſts,</hi> and are ſaid to have <hi>fellowſhip with divels</hi> others that <hi>ſchiſmed in their love feaſts,</hi> and inordinate cleaving to their Sectory teachers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing <hi>Paul,</hi> yea, and ſome whoſe emulations, contentions and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, was not repented of in a long time; and yet he giveth no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 20. 21.</note> for the excommunicating any more then he which had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a ſin. which the very light of nature condemneth.</p>
               <p>If no ſinnes might be borne in the Church then Chriſt, when he <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> gave direction to proceed againſt <hi>ſins and ſinners,</hi> would have uſed the ſame word which <hi>Paul</hi> doth, which ſignifieth <hi>infirmity,</hi> or <hi>feebleneſſe of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 18. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 18. 19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 7. 1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2. 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 4. 5. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26. 2. &amp; 27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 29. &amp; 16. 4. &amp; 19. 29. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>mind,</hi> and not that which <hi>Iohn</hi> uſeth, which ſignifieth a <hi>ſcandall;</hi> for both Chriſt in the rule, and <hi>Paul</hi> in his direction for practice, ſpeake of ſuch evils as are notorious and ſcandalous. Secondly, <hi>David</hi> is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taxed for ſcandall in all the infirmities he ſhewed at <hi>Nob, Gath,</hi> and in the matters of <hi>loab, ziha, Mephiboſheth</hi> and others. but only in the matters of adultery and murther, with <hi>Bat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſheba</hi> and <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iah,</hi> he is ſaid to ſcandall, or lay a ſtumbling blocke.</p>
               <p>If no ſins in the Church may be borne, how could <hi>David</hi> ſay, <hi>Who can tell the errors of this life;</hi> or <hi>how oft he offendeth?</hi> and againe, <hi>The</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>righteous falleth ſeven times a day, and riſeth againe;</hi> and that of <hi>Iames, In</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143. 2. <hi>Iam.</hi> 3. 1. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>many things we ſinne all, &amp;c.</hi> We may not thinke that the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were either ignorant of groſſe evils. or fell ſeven times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day into them but that they had their continuall failings in inferiour and doubtfull things, and having ſo, if they were now alive, belike they were not good enough for the ſtrict ſeparation, that fall ſo often, and into ſo many things as they did.</p>
               <p>Indeed, the example of theſe holy men thus complaining may lead us all to a more thorow ſearch of our ſelves; for if they pronounced ſuch a ſentence upon themſelves, much more may we if we looke
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119581:38"/> well to it; and what mad men are we to quarrell and ſtrive with our neighbours and brethren for their infirmities when we have ſuch in our ſelves, for groſſe and ſcandalous evils indeed, we may and muſt ſtrive, for all good men have not ſuch in themſelves.</p>
               <p>If no ſins muſt be borne with, then no two men in this world could <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> walke together in Chriſtian fellowſhip, no, not any man with his wife, nor no father with his child, neither can any Church fellowſhip if they be true to this ground, poſſible hold together; for no men can converſe much together, but they ſhall ſee ſome fault in each other either in omiſſion or commiſſion. One man will be too remiſſe and <note place="margin">Some things amiſſe in the beſt men.</note> cold in family duties of inſtruction, prayer, &amp;c. Another too ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh in hearing, Sacraments and other publique exerciſes; one man is too full of worldly cares, another is too careleſſe in his world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affaires; one man even kills himſelfe with hard labour: another ſpoyles himſelfe with too much idleneſſe; one man is too talkative and buſie, another is too mute and ſilent. At a word, in all men there is to be ſeene ſome partiality, ſome pride, ſome conceitedneſſe, ſome ſelfe-love, ſome follie, ſome ignorance, ſome error and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoundneſſe, ſome anger and impatience, all which are evills, and will more or leſſe appeare in men, whileſt they live, notwithſtanding all admonitions ad cenſures that can be paſt upon them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore except we will by excommunication caſt the Church out of the Church, we muſt cover their infirmities in love, as they muſt alſo ours; and bury them in a loving delight in their graces, exhorting <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 32. 33.</note> and perſwading them, but not provoking, biting or cenſuring them, but freely forgiving them, as God for Chriſts ſake freely forgiveth us.</p>
               <p>If no ſins muſt be borne, then there muſt be perfection, even in this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> life, either in truth, or in conceit; for they they that are perſwaded that other men doe cover their failings in love, will as lovingly cover <note place="margin">No perfection in this life.</note> other mens againe, ſeeing it is worſe then beaſt-like, not to give love for love; indeed, one man hath a more prying and piercing eye to ſee into his neighbours faults, then his neighbour hath to ſee into his, and ſo he is apt to pleaſe himſelfe, as if he were not as other men are, but he whoſe infirmities are moſt of all ript up and raked into, is <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4. <hi>Luke</hi> 1 &amp; 11. 14. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 10. 15.</note> oftentimes <hi>rather juſtified before God,</hi> then the other, to whom nothing is ſpoken; and indeed, he which truly examineth and ſearcheth into himſelfe, cannot poſſibly be voyd of charity towards others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:119581:39"/>
               <head>What kind of ſinnes and ſinners they be that may be borne in the Church.</head>
               <p>THat ſome ſins then may be borne and covered in love in the <note place="margin">SECT. 30.</note> Church and amongſt Chriſtians, is out of queſtion, and that ſome other ſins may not be borne, is alſo certaine, but to ſet downe every particular ſin which is to be borne, and every particular for which men muſt be abandoned without repentance, were impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and meere trifling; for when we oppoſe godly men, and wicked men, we doe not meane that they onely are godly which never doe <note place="margin">A godly and an ungodly man deſcribed.</note> nothing but what is godly; nor they only wicked, which never doe ought but wickedneſſe; for there is no man ſo good, but that he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times falleth into ſome evill, nor none ſo wicked, but hee ſometimes ſtumbleth upon ſome good. It is indeed the common and cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry courſe in practiſing groſſe evill, and refuſing to doe good, that proveth a man to be wicked, and the frequent performance of good duties and ordinary abſtinence from evills, that ſhewes a man to be <note place="margin">Godlineſſe and wickedneſſe are two ſeverall trades.</note> godly; for as one ſaith, evill men can doe good by accident, and good men by accident fall into evill, but the common trade of a godly man is to doe good, and of a wicked man to doe evill.</p>
               <p>Indeed, ſuch ſins as under the Law were death, as Inceſt, Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Blaſphemy, &amp;c. being now committed by any in the Church, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 21. 12. <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. 29. &amp; 19. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; 24. 14. <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 22. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 13. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9. 10.</note> they repent, they may, and muſt be <hi>caſt out,</hi> but otherwiſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they be ſuch as the light of nature condemneth, or ſuch as the Scripture in expreſſe termes forbiddeth, and threatneth to ſhut <hi>out of Heaven</hi> for them, men ſhould be wary how they excommunicate for them; and although by this rule few would be excommunicate in Churches that are made of fit matter, and the fewer the better, ſo long as groſſe wiekednes is not there harboured; for it is better to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in too much lenity, then in too much ſeverity; better to let ſome <hi>tares ſtand,</hi> then to plucke up the good wheat; for though Chriſt have <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. 28. 29.</note> given that ſharp and ſevere cenſure into the hands of his Saints, yet they muſt take heed they be not too buſie with it, ſharpe inſtruments muſt be skilfully and warily handled; and though Chriſt have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to <hi>binde in Heaven,</hi> ſuch as his Church <hi>bindeth on earth,</hi> yet this promiſe muſt be reſtrained onely to ſuch caſes as wherein the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 18. 19.</note> is deſerved, for elſe the Church rather bindes over it ſelfe to the wrath of God for wronging his ſervants, and abuſing his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and <hi>taking his name in vaine,</hi> then commits the perſon either to <note place="margin">Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt be uſed warily.</note> Satan or Gods wrath; ſo that we muſt be ſure to ſee that the caſe be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119581:39"/> juſt before we cenſure; and if the Word of God have not ſaid, that ſuch ſhall <hi>be ſhut out of Heaven,</hi> we muſt moderate our zeale, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine our paſſions, and not thinke to make Chriſt follow us, but we <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 36.</note> muſt follow him, and <hi>be mercifull as he is mercifull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as in civill judgements, death is never inflicted juſtly, but <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> for ſome groſſe and haynous crimes; ſo in the ſpirituall judgements <note place="margin">Men muſt not be hanged for trifles.</note> of the Church, excommunication, which is the moſt ſevereſt cenſure that a Church can have, ſhould not be adminiſtred upon any, but for ſuch haynous evills, which being perſiſted in, doe barre a man for ever out of Gods Kingdome.</p>
               <p>Indeed, ſome peremptory and preſumptuous men have got ſuch a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> habit of bitterneſſe, that they thinke their ſpeech is of no force, except <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 11. 2. 6. Peremptory cenſurers dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</note> they fling the <hi>fire brands of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll</hi> at every one whom they deale againſt, though the matter be ſmall, and ſometimes alſo doubtfull and diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and it is well ſuch kinde of men keepe not the keyes of heaven gate for if they did, none but themſelves ſhould come there; and if alſo they had civill power, I know not what <hi>havocke</hi> they would make amongſt ſome men that are better then themſelves.</p>
               <p>Many of the ſeparation complaine (as they may) of oppreſſion by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> civill power; and wrong by penall ſtatutes and commiſſioners ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences <note place="margin">Vnjuſt excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication more evill then civill oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28: 9.</note> by which often they are impriſoned, baniſhed, and ſometimes put to death. And ſurely, though theſe things are done by their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites <hi>in a rage that goeth up to heaven,</hi> which the Lord, no doubt, will one day call to reckoning; yet it is alſo juſt with God to pay them home wiih bloody and bodily cruelty, which ſpare not to racke teare, and turmoyle the ſoules and conſciences of their brethren by oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious and bitter ſpeeches, and violent and dangerous cenſures un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Three cautions concluding the Doctrine of forbearance.</head>
               <p>TO conclude, wee muſt alwayes beare in mind, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <note place="margin">SECT. 31.</note> have in them in all places a double ſentence and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of ſuch things as they treat of, the one cleare and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 13. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15, 16. 20.</note> the other probable and doubtfull.</p>
               <p>In the things which the Scripture it ſelfe clearely determineth, we may boldly proceed to profeſſe and practiſe accordingly; but where there is but a bare probabilitie in the Scripture, we muſt be wary what we doe, for a hundred probabilities doe not conclude a certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: neither is it ſufficient that we have ſome <hi>rever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> mens gloſſes and <note place="margin">No Expoſitor ſound but the Holy Ghoſt.</note> gueſſes to goe before us; for when all is done, if the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> be not both Text man and Comment, and conclude the point ſome where,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119581:40"/> either in plaine words, or ordinary examples, we are as farre off from the matter as before, and doe rather bundle up more ignorance with our ancients in taking things from their mouths and pens then bring any honour either to the truth or them.</p>
               <p>And for a man to uſe either wit or learning, to make the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſeeme to ſpeake that which it doth not indeed ſpeake, is rather a vanity than a vertue, and how much was Chriſt offended for <hi>Peters</hi> ſnatching at a doubtfull word; as alſo what a fearefull ſin did thoſe <hi>witneſſes</hi> run into that came againſt Chriſt, by wreſting an ambiguous <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. 22. 23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 61.</note> phraſe to their owne advantage?</p>
               <p>In things therefore probable and doubtfull, it better becomes us to ſeeme ignorant, then to grow preſumptuous, and rather conclude againſt our ſelves, that we know nothing as we ought to know it, but <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 2. 13. 9.</note> have our knowledge in part, as is our obedience, then preſume above that which is ſober and mute, or imagine that we know and can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 3.</note> all things.</p>
               <p>And as wee muſt be ſparing and modeſt in determining ſuch points, as wherein the Scripture is doubtfull, ſo wee muſt be much <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> more ſparing in uſing any violent or cruell words or practices againſt men in matters doubtfull, yea, though in thy apprehenſion it be cleare in the letter of the Scriptures, yet if thorow cuſtome and ignorance of our times, it be growne a matter queſtionable, and that amongſt godly men, as was once <hi>Polygamy</hi> amongſt the Fathers, and <hi>Fornication</hi> among <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 21. 15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 18. <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 29.</note> the Churches of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> though thou muſt retraine it thy ſelfe in conſcience of God yet muſt uſe no violent words or practice where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to force all others to doe like thee.</p>
               <p>And ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if thy neighbour or thy brother, hold or practiſe any thing which thou judgeſt amiſſe, except thou have an expreſſe Scripture, <note place="margin">3,</note> whereby to ſtrike the matter dead, and out of which thou canſt ſay, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> it is better to be ſilent then to uſe much diſputing; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 9. 8. 9. 10. 13.</note> for witty and <hi>Logicall</hi> diſputes ſerve more often to feed light and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt affections, then to ſettle a ſound judgement, yea, and men upon a little ſnatch therein, are apt to let their wits a plodding about every nice and triviall queſtion whileſt better things paſſe by them, or are ſtolne and loſt out of their mindes; Beſides, except the reaſons brought againſt an opinion be cleare and ſtrongly backed by evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence <note place="margin">Subtile diſputes more dangerous then profitable.</note> of Scripture, they rather ſtrengthen the perſons in their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then draw them from it, neither will ever the truth and Church of God be ſettled and ſtabliſhed, either by outward violence or ſubtill diſputes, but if a certaine and expreſſe word cannot be brought, to put to ſilence a mans contradictory opinion the only way is to let him alone, and to goe on lovingly and brotherly with him in the fellowſhip of his other graces, till God <hi>reveale further,</hi> putting <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil</hi> 3. 15.</note> aſide all occaſion of ſpeech about that wherein the difference lieth,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119581:40"/> leſt from talking you fall to chiding, and from chiding to bitter ſtrife, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 15. <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 38, 39.</note> hatred and heart-burning, to the weakning of your comfort with God, and the hindering of your favour and reſpect with men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Concluſion and Summe of all.</head>
               <p>NOw although I have written much, and that with all plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <note place="margin">SECT. 32.</note> that I can, yet I live amidſt ſo many ſleepers and drouſie Chriſtians, that me thinketh, I heare ſome ſtarting up about <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ben. Sirach. cap.</hi> 22. 20.</note> mine eares, and asking me <hi>what i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is I have ſaid,</hi> and what I would have, and therefore I will ſumme up all my aime in a word.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I finde in this world two ſorts of men, <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>godly,</hi> and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> both theſe muſt live in one <hi>world,</hi> but not in one Church. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>Iohn</hi> 17. 14. 16. <hi>Act.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 44. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 47 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 16. 17. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 8. 23 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4. 23. 24. <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 5. &amp; 14. 23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 4. 12. <hi>Acts</hi> 21 13. 14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 25. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 17. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 42. 44. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. 1. 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>godly</hi> I would have to gather themſelves together, and combine in a ſpirituall fellowſhip, apart from the vaine world, and wicked therein a bandoning all mans inventions, worſhipping God onely by his Word and Graces, chooſing their owne <hi>Miniſters,</hi> executing <hi>Diſcipline</hi> amongſt themſelves, and rather loſe their lives, then loſe this liberty; but to continue feaſting and feeding together in the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Gods ſacred Ordinances all the time of their dwelling in this <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> even till they are tranſlated to the mount of glory.</p>
               <p>Secondly, And becauſe the policie of the times will allow no ſuch things, but compells as well the <hi>uncircumciſed Philiſtins,</hi> and the <hi>blacke</hi> mouthed <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hiopian,</hi> to the <hi>Temple</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> as the ſons of <hi>Abraham,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 48. <hi>Rom.</hi> 21. 27.</note> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> of the Lord; impoſing alſo upon them other officers, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, Traditions and Ceremonies, then ever the infallible wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of Chriſt or his Apoſtles mentioned:</p>
               <p>Therfore I have exhorted all that feare God to reſolve to ſuffer with patience and courage all ſuch oppreſſions and perſecutions, as for their abſtinence from the aforeſaid evills, or practiſing the contrary good ſhall be impoſed and afflicted upon them by any authority <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 27. <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 22, 23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 12. <hi>Acts</hi> 7 90. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 44 45.</note> whatſoever, and as meeke and gentle Lambes to goe with <hi>Chriſt to the Croſſe,</hi> and with the Apoſtles to the priſon, even with gentle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties, and earneſt prayers for their oppoſites that ſo advancing the glory and name of Chriſt here in this world, they may ſit for ever in glory with him in heaven.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, And ſeeing the ſtraggling opinions and oppoſite practices <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of ſome godly men, is a maine hinderance hereof, therefore I have propoſed certaine wayes whereby the overſtrained heat of the ſtrict <note place="margin">A harmony in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</note> ſeparation may be mitigated and ordered; and the ſluggiſh confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the profeſſors awaked and revived, that both may re-unite
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119581:41"/> together, and converſe ſweetly in one Church, as the Lord hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them one heaven.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, And becauſe the vaine heart of man is ſubject to be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> lifted up with it's owne conceits and perſwaſions, and to be vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt others for every ſmall difference, therefore I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and proved the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>forbearance,</hi> by many infallible grounds; and have ſhewed, that it is the duty of all Chriſtians <hi>to ſerve one another in love,</hi> and continue their fellowſhip in the free and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 14. 25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 1.</note> familiar uſe of that knowledge and gifts wherein they agree, without entring into any tedious and doubtfull controverſies, to diſturbe and provoke one another, much leſſe <hi>abuſe, revile</hi> and <hi>abandon</hi> one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 36.</note> remembring that the Word <hi>of God came not to</hi> one <hi>Church</hi> or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alone, but others have underſtanding as well as they, and the moſt confident ſpeaker is oftentimes more awry than <hi>hee that keepes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 12. 3. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 13. 14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 1. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſilence,</hi> however the largeſt knowledge muſt have the largeſt love, leſt whileſt wee thinke to teach, wee doe nothing but devoure and make havocke.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119581:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
